<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse concerning the nominal and real trinitarians</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11199837</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11199837</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36090)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1439:56)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse concerning the nominal and real trinitarians</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46702:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning the <hi>Nominal and Real</hi> Trinitarians.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non Partûm Studiis agimur, ſed ſumſimus arma</l>
               <l>Conſiliis inimica tuis, Diſcordia vecors.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:46702:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46702:2"/>
            <head>Of the Nominal, and Real TRINITARIANS.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Diſtinction of <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> into <hi>Nominals</hi> and <hi>Realiſts;</hi> and the Deſign of theſe Sheets.</head>
               <p>IT will eaſily appear, to all that have ſeen the late Prints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Trinitarians and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians; That the Queſtions controverted between us, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged here, <hi>on another Foot</hi> as they ſpeak, in <hi>another</hi> Method, and by <hi>different</hi> Arguments, than in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts, or by the Latin Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Among other remarks that we have made and urged, the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> ſhow; That their Oppoſers do indeed all go under the common name of <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> but are (in truth) a great many ſeveral and contrary Sects. They all caſt up their Caps, and cry, <hi>Trinity, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> But the Ideas they have of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and conſequently their <hi>Faiths</hi> concerning this (pretended) Myſtery, are ſo many and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; that they are leſs one Party among themſelves, than the far more Learned, and far greater Number of them (I mean hereby, the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Trinitarians) are one Party with Us. As much as the Socinians are clamour'd on, for (abominable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable) Hereticks; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certain than that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Trinitarians, who are truly and properly <hi>the Church,</hi> and who are by much the Majority of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, are altogether in the ſame Sentiments concerning Almighty GOD, and the Perſon of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; that we are.</p>
               <p>This is one of the Points that I ſhall inſiſt on, and evince in theſe Sheets: but I ſhall argue divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Matters, theſe two eſpecially. That the ſeveral Sects of <hi>Real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> are guilty of a manifeſt Tritheiſm, their Doctrine (neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily and immediately) infers three Gods: and that the <hi>Nominal Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> have cauſleſly innovated <hi>the Language</hi> of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of the (Primitive) Church, concerning GOD, and the Perſon of the Lord Chriſt. I ſaid, <hi>in the Language</hi> of Scripture, and of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46702:3"/>antient Church; for they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Primitive and true <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> only they have not kept to <hi>the Form of ſound Words.</hi> I will ſpeak, firſt, of (our Brethren) the <hi>Nominal Trinitarians;</hi> then of the Tritheiſtick Tribes, or <hi>Realiſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Nominal Trinitarians; that theſe are the Church.</head>
               <p>THE firſt obſervation to be made on <hi>the Nominals,</hi> is; that theſe are <hi>the Church;</hi> which I prove by two (inconteſtable) Arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Doctrine has been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed by <hi>a General Council.</hi> The Council aſſembled at the <hi>Lateran,</hi> in the Year 1215, eſtabliſhed (in the moſt ample manner, and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Terms) the Doctrine of the School-Divines or <hi>Nominal Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> and condemns, in the Perſon and Writings of <hi>Abbat Joachim,</hi> the Doctrine of the <hi>Real Trinitarians,</hi> as <hi>Heretical</hi> and <hi>Mad;</hi> I uſe the very words of the <hi>2d</hi> Canon of that Council. To this Argument, I muſt note two things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> This Council was more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>General,</hi> than almoſt any of the Councils that are ſo called. Here were preſent 1200 Fathers; the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the Emperour of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> the King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the Kings of <hi>France, England, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon, Hungary, Jeruſalem, Cyprus,</hi> and divers others: Here alſo were the five Patriarchs, (partly in Perſon, partly by their Legats) <hi>the Roman, Conſtantinopolitan,</hi> he of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Antiochian</hi> and <hi>Alexandrian;</hi> whoſe Preſence (by themſelves or their Legats) is ſuppoſed neceſſary towards conſtituting an Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal (or General) Council.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Divines and Canoniſts do not give the name of <hi>Hereſy</hi> to any Doctrine, becauſe 'tis rejected by a great number of <hi>Learned Men,</hi> or by <hi>a National Council:</hi> but they reckon it Hereſy, if it has been cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by <hi>a General Council,</hi> which repreſents <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church.</hi> Be the miſtake never ſo great, let it have been condemned by never ſo many Writers; whether Fathers or Moderns, or both: 'tis only Error, 'tis not Hereſy, unleſs it has been Anathematiz'd by the Catholick (or Univerſal) Church; and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church is never underſtood to ſpeak, but by a General Council; which for that reaſon is called <hi>the Church Repreſentative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Briefly,</hi> Hereſy and the Faith can be declared, but <hi>only by a General Council;</hi> the General Council at the Lateran (in <hi>Rome</hi>) has avowed the Doctrine of the <hi>Nominal Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and Anathematiz'd the Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis and Explication of the <hi>Real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians:</hi> therefore, ſay I, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are the Church; the latter are Hereticks. I am amazed, when I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46702:3"/>hear ſome <hi>Real Trinitarians</hi> ſay in their Books; That the Doctrine of the <hi>Nominals</hi> never had any other publick Authority, but the Creed and <hi>2d</hi> Canon of the Council of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran:</hi> for what other <hi>equal</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereto can it have; is not a General Council the higheſt Court of the Church? Her Canons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the <hi>Faith,</hi> her Anathemas <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy.</hi> And what other Council ever was ſo General as this; in which were aſſembled, the Emperour, and Kings of the Eaſt and Weſt, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and Greek Churches, 1200 Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and what eſpecially makes a General Council, the five Patriarchs of Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>What will the <hi>Realiſts</hi> ſay here; that this was <hi>a Popiſh Council?</hi> Firſt, it would be News indeed, that the Roman Catholicks are not Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, in the Queſtions concerning the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the <hi>Incarnation.</hi> It has ever been granted to them, both by the <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts,</hi> and Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they are ſound in Fundamentals; in the Doctrines of the Trinity, the Incarnation, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and ſuch like: their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror conſiſts, in the Additions they have made to the Fundamentals; and namely, by their Doctrines of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, Tranſubſtantiation, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Invocation of Images and Saints, and the reſt. And is the Greek Church alſo Heretical in the Doctrine of the Trinity? for in this Council, the Greek Emperour and Church were repreſented, as well as the Latin Church: nay, of the five Patriarchs here preſent, four of them belong to the Orient, or Greek Church. When the Realiſts have turned themſelves all ways, they will find themſelves held, and even bound by the Authority of this Council; which is too Great and Venerable to be (openly, or directly) diſclaimed.</p>
               <p>'Tis objected to this Council, by Mr. <hi>Spanheim,</hi> the preſent (Learned) Profeſſor at <hi>Leyden;</hi> that they aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, and publiſhed 70 Canons in 20 days Time; and that the Canons were not framed by the Fathers, but by the Pope. Theſe are frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Exceptions, unworthy of ſo Learned an Hiſtorian: for 'tis not at all to the purpoſe, who contrived theſe Canons; ſeeing they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, aſſented to, and publiſhed by the Council. Canons are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times compoſed by ſome particular Father in a Council; ſometimes by a Committee of the Council, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as in the preſent Caſe) by the Preſident: but by whomſoever they are drawn up, they are not the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of that Perſon or Perſons; but of the Council, when the Council has examined, approved and voted them. But Mr. <hi>Spanheim</hi> doth not find Fault with this Council, for their Explication of the Doctrine of the Trinity, or the Canons that refer to any part of that Article; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was convened, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence indeed to carry on the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> in the Holy Land; but really to raiſe a Cruſade (or Holy War) againſt the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and to confirm the Vaſſalage of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46702:4"/>
                  <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt the Conſent of the Engliſh Peerage; that is (in ſhort) to inlarge the Juriſdiction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Authority of the Weſtern Patriarch, or Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. My ſecond (as I ſaid, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable) Proof, that <hi>the Nominal Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians</hi> are the Church, is, that the <hi>Divinity-Chairs,</hi> and all <hi>Writers,</hi> whether of <hi>Controverſy,</hi> or <hi>Syſtems,</hi> have ever followed the Doctrine of the Schools (which is the Doctrine of the <hi>Nominal Trinitarians</hi>) and the Creed, and <hi>2d</hi> Canon of the (before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Doctrine of the Trinity. They all take it, as the <hi>Council-Schools</hi> and <hi>Nominals</hi> do, for their Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That <q rend="inline">there is but one only and ſelf-ſame Divine Subſtance: and in that Subſtance, but one (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite) Undeſtanding, but one (almighty) Energy, and Will, <hi>in number.</hi>
                  </q> Which is to ſay, there is but one really <hi>Subſiſting</hi> (divine) Perſon, or God is but one <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon;</hi> tho in a Critical or Claſſical Senſe of the word <hi>Perſons,</hi> namely, when <hi>Perſons</hi> is uſed only for <hi>various Relations</hi> of the ſame really <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> we may ſay there are three Divine Perſons. A <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon</hi> is (by Confeſſion of all) one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Subſtance, having (one) Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will and Energy (or power of Action) in number: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God being (according to the Council, Schools, and all Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals) one Subſtance, or one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſpiritual Subſtance, with one only Underſtanding, Energy and Will; he can be, according to them, but one <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> tho he may be more Metaphyſical or Claſſical Perſons, that is, more Relations or Properties. This, I ſay, is the Doctrine of that Council, of the Schools, and of the <hi>Nominal Trinitarians;</hi> and it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been approved and taught by the Divinity-Chairs, and by the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters both of Syſtems and Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy; therefore the Nominals, not the Realiſts, are the Church.</p>
               <p>I ſhall grant, that the real Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians have on their ſide, the moſt (and moſt conſiderable) of <hi>the Fathers;</hi> reckoning from about the Year of Chriſt 140, and meaning thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe Writings have been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to come down to our Times; and excepting out of the Number, the Party in the firſt <hi>Nicen</hi> Council, which ſome little time after the breaking up of that Council, were conſidered as the Orthodox Party, and the Church, and were perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſuch by the <hi>Arians:</hi> But the Nominals have what is much more conſiderable, all <hi>the Moderns;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the Moderns from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran,</hi> or the Year 1215. Since that Council, Learning, and more eſpecially Theological Learning, has not only been revived, but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improved; the later Divines have been better Criticks, Interpreters, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, than the Fathers were; and the two laſt Ages only, have afforded more Hundreds of able Divines, than there were ſingle Perſons of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Of the Latin Fathers, only
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46702:4"/>St. <hi>Jerem</hi> would have been account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Learned Divine in our Age; and of the Greeks, <hi>Origen, Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the two <hi>Gregories, Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> and four or five more: had the reſt wrote in any part of the two laſt Ages, they ſhould undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly have been reckoned among <hi>the Scriblers.</hi> The <hi>Nominals</hi> therefore, if you demand <hi>Authority,</hi> produce a General Council, not only eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing their Hypotheſis, or Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Trinity, but denounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Anathema</hi> to the contrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and <hi>the Realiſts:</hi> if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>a Poll,</hi> if you will be judged by moſt Votes, they have for them an hundred (far more Learned) <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns,</hi> againſt one <hi>Father</hi> who can be cited for their Oppoſers, the <hi>Realiſts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Why the <hi>Nominals</hi> are ſo called; their Doctrine, and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the <hi>Unitarians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Church then, as I ſaid, is unqueſtionably <hi>the Nominal Party;</hi> and this Party is ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as <hi>the Realiſts</hi> are denominated from their believing three diſtinct Divine Spirits or Minds, who are ſo many <hi>real ſubſiſting Perſons:</hi> ſo the <hi>Nominals</hi> believe three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who are <hi>Perſons in Name only,</hi> indeed and in truth they are but <hi>one ſubſiſting Perſon.</hi> This will appear by all more fully and clearly, by the account I ſhall now give (in their own Words and Terms) of their Doctrine, Hypotheſis, or Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>The Nominals are one Party in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Subdiviſions; they muſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one Party, becauſe their Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſo far agree, as really to leave but one God, and one Divine Perſon <hi>properly and phyſically ſo called.</hi> All the Diviſions of the <hi>Nominals</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that there is but one <hi>only</hi> and <hi>ſelf-ſame</hi> Divine Eſſence and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Divine Subſtance accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, is <hi>one in Number:</hi> not, as the Realiſts hold, <hi>one in Properties only;</hi> which indeed were only <hi>a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of Subſtances, not <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> As the Divine Subſtance is numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally One, ſo (according to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals) is the Divine Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Energy, and Will; they are not repeated as the Perſons are, but they are one as ſtrictly and properly, as the Eſſence or Subſtance is one: Or more clearly, if it may be, thus; as there is but one Divine ſpiritual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo there is but one (omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) Underſtanding, but one (omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent) Energy, but one (moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Will. They allow indeed of three Perſons in the Senſe hereafter declared; but all theſe Perſons have but one Underſtanding, one Will, one Energy in Number. Having laid this honeſt and ſound Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they take a Latitude, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out quarrelling with, or cenſuring
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46702:5"/>one another, in declaring what is to be meant by the three Perſons. One ſaith, they are only three Acts of God, whereby he is denominated af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three ſeveral manners. On the account of his Creating, Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Sanctifying Mankind, he is called three Perſons: for (ſay theſe Gentlemen) a Creator is a Perſon, a Redeemer is a Perſon, a Sanctifier is a Perſon. If you reply, true; but one Perſon may perform all theſe Acts, and ſuſtain all theſe Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: they anſwer, you have right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood them, for they intend not to ſay, there are three (Divine) <hi>phyſical</hi> or <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſons, but three Perſons in a Critical or Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical (or if you will, Metaphyſical) ſenſe of the word Perſons. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, three ſuch Perſons as one Man, who happens to be a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Husband,</hi> and a <hi>Father,</hi> may be ſaid to be. Every Body knows who is that Learned <hi>Profeſſor</hi> that preached this Trinity, firſt in three <hi>Sermons</hi> to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> with great applauſe; afterwards maintained it with no leſs Approbation among the <hi>London</hi> Divines, in divers <hi>Letters</hi> by him publiſhed. The <hi>Socinians,</hi> not only never denied three ſuch Perſons in God, or ſuch a Trinity, but as willingly avow it, as this Profeſſor himſelf, his Learned Auditory at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> or his Admirers at <hi>London.</hi> Why are <hi>we</hi> Hereticks, while <hi>he</hi> is not only confeſt to be Orthodox, and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, but is eſteemed as (a worthy and deſerving) <hi>Apologiſt for the Faith?</hi> Why may not the Author of the <hi>Brief Notes on the Creed of Athanaſius,</hi> or he of the <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations on the Explications and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of the Trinity,</hi> ſucceed to this Profeſſor in his Canonſhip, at <hi>Chriſt-Church?</hi> It cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that could they but prevaricate, they might paſs for as Orthodox, and as ſound Trinitarians, as the very greateſt and bittereſt of their Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niators: their Faith concerning God is the ſame, both for Senſe and Terms; but the Profeſſor, though a real U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarian, and only a Nominal Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarian, can <hi>aſperſe Socinus,</hi> they (on the contrary) ſee no reaſon to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim their Friends and Partiſans.</p>
               <p>Other <hi>Nominals</hi> ſoar high; they explain their Trinity after a very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and ſurprizing manner. The Father, ſay they, is <hi>the Fountain of the Deity,</hi> the Author and the Cauſe of the other two Perſons; he is <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Mind and Wiſdom:</hi> who from all Eternity moſt perfectly <hi>underſtood</hi> himſelf and his own Perfections, and alſo <hi>Willed</hi> (that is, Loved) himſelf in a moſt perfect manner. No one will doubt (ſay they) that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, or from all Eternity, perfectly underſtood himſelf: and 'tis Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Connate to every Being that hath Underſtanding, to Will (or Love) himſelf; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Self-love</hi> is an Affection naturally ariſing in intellectual Beings; 'tis the firſt Affection of ſuch Beings, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres inſeparably to them. But ſeeing whatſoever underſtandeth, doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by conceiving within it ſelf <hi>an Image</hi> of the thing underſtood;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46702:5"/>therefore the Father (as hath been ſaid) underſtanding himſelf from all Eternity, conceived within himſelf (from all Eternity) a moſt <hi>perfect I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of himſelf. Which Image, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thus conceived, and as it were <hi>generated</hi> by him, is called <hi>the Son;</hi> 'tis alſo called the Wiſdom of God, <hi>hiſ reflex Wiſdom,</hi> becauſe 'tis the Wiſdom that <hi>reſulteth</hi> from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's underſtanding himſelf, and his own Perfections. As God under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth, he <hi>Willeth</hi> alſo (or Loveth) himſelf: this ſecond Act, or God's Loving himſelf, is the Holy Spirit or third Perſon; as underſtanding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (or the <hi>reflex</hi> Wiſdom of <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Mind and Wiſdom) was the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Perſon of the Trinity. To un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand one ſelf, and to love (or will) one ſelf in created and finite Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are but <hi>only Acts of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and Will;</hi> but in God, we call them Perſons. Though nothing can be more ridiculous, than this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a Trinity; yet to purchaſe their quiet, the Socinians are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>to wear a ſtrange, and odd Badg.</hi> For Peace-ſake, they will ſay with our Holy Mother the Church, Underſtanding (or <hi>reflex Wiſdom</hi>) is a Perſon, and <hi>Love</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon; and theſe two, with <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Wiſdom,</hi> ſhall be called <hi>a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Indeed we could wiſh, that ſo grave a Matron as the Church, would leave off Trifling: but ſeeing for the main of it, the thing is true; for 'tis true, that the Father is <hi>original Mind</hi> or Wiſdom, and <hi>he <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> and <hi>Willeth</hi> himſelf; we can bear with a little impropriety in ſpeaking of Things. The Church requires us to ſay, Father, Son and Spirit, Trinity, three Divine Perſons, but ſhe declares at the ſame time, that the meaning only is, <hi>God</hi> (or original Mind) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeth and Loveth himſelf:</hi> it would be hard if Sons ſhould contend with a Mother, about a few <hi>(uncouth, or ill-choſe)</hi> Terms and Words, on which ſhe (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly) puts a ſober meaning, a Senſe no way contrary to the Unity of God, or that there is in truth but one <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> Divine Perſon.</p>
               <p>Well, here are two Explications of the Trinity, by the <hi>Nominals.</hi> The firſt ſaith, the Trinity of Divine Perſons are the three <hi>external</hi> Acts of Creation, Redemption, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; or God conſidered as the Creator, the Redeemer, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of the World, or of Mankind. The other ſaith, the ſecond and third Perſons of the Trinity, are indeed three Acts of God, but they are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> Acts, even his Underſtanding and Loving himſelf: So that the whole Trinity is <hi>original Mind</hi> (or the <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſon of the Father) <hi>Knowing</hi> and <hi>Willing</hi> himſelf; ſo theſe two Parties. But another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the <hi>Nominals</hi> tell us, the Divine Perſons are not bare Acts of God, whether External or Internal, but they are three <hi>Attributes</hi> of God: Goodneſs, Wiſdom, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſay they, are that Trinity which the Church teaches; and ſhe teaches no other. But then, ſay I, 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent again, that the Church and the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46702:6"/>Socinians are well agreed; for the latter, no leſs than the former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Trinity; and the only Hereticks in theſe Queſtions, are the <hi>Real Trinitarians,</hi> who believe a Trinity of three really <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> three <hi>diſtinct Spirits,</hi> three (Almighty, All-knowing) Beings.</p>
               <p>But they are not very many, tho they are Learned Men, that ſpeak af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe manners: the School-men, and the Divines that follow them, and who more properly are the Nominal Party, deliver themſelves in other Terms; though in the main, in what truly gives to them the Name of <hi>Nominal Trinitarians,</hi> all the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them perfectly agree. Becauſe we litigate in the Engliſh Tongue, and conteſt theſe Queſtions only with Engliſh Writers; it will be fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Doctrine of the Schools, or the Party which (I ſaid) are more properly (it may be) the Nominal Trinitarians, out of the late Books of Dr. <hi>S</hi>—<hi>th</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi> They teach, that God or the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is one (Numerical ſelf-ſame) Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Divine Subſtance, one (only) Spirit, one (ſolitary) Being. And though he is three Perſons (by which, what they mean we ſhall ſee preſently); there is in the whole Trinty but one (infinite) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> one (ſoveraign) <hi>Will,</hi> one (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty) <hi>Energy</hi> or Power of Action in <hi>Number.</hi> This one Divine <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectual Subſtance,</hi> or really <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> is (at it were) diſtinguiſhed and diverſified by three <hi>relative Modes,</hi> or <hi>relative Subſiſtences:</hi> which Subſiſtences or Modes are ſo intirely <hi>Relative,</hi> that their very <hi>Subſiſtence is nothing elſe but their Relation;</hi> their Relation is not ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent upon, or ſupervenient to their Subſiſtence, as in created Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but is one and the ſame with it. Theſe relative Modes being three in Number, are the three <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonalities</hi> of the Deity; but the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete</hi> and <hi>abſtract</hi> Terms (namely Perſonalities and Perſons) are but only different ways of expreſſing the ſame thing. And therefore as we deſcribe the <hi>Perſonalities</hi> in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, by <hi>Relations;</hi> relative <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtences,</hi> relative <hi>Modes,</hi> relative <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties,</hi> or ſuch like: So we ſay alſo that every <hi>Perſon</hi> (as well as every <hi>Perſonality</hi>) <hi>in the Trinity is wholly Relative;</hi> that is, that which makes the firſt Perſon in the Trinity to be <hi>a Perſon,</hi> makes him to be <hi>a Father;</hi> and what makes him to be <hi>a Father,</hi> makes him to be a Perſon; ſo that (as we have but now ſaid) both Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Perſonalities in the Trinity are <hi>meerly Relations,</hi> or relative Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the one (ſelf-ſame) Divine Subſtance, Being, or Spirit. Theſe three relative Modes, Relations, or relative Properties, in the Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Godhead, are <hi>Innaſcibility</hi> or Paternity, <hi>paſſive Generation,</hi> and <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Spiration;</hi> in plainer Engliſh, to <hi>Beget,</hi> to be <hi>Begotten,</hi> and to Proceed or be <hi>Breathed:</hi> the firſt maketh the Perſon of the Father, the other two make or conſtitute the Son and Holy Spirit. This is the Sum of what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46702:6"/>Doctor <hi>S</hi>—<hi>th</hi> ſaith in his laſt Book, or <hi>Tritheiſm Charged,</hi> pag. 156, 157. Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> (Author of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Policy) expreſſes this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, though not ſo fully, yet more intelligibly to the Unlearned, in theſe words. <q rend="inline">The Subſtance of God, with this property <hi>to be of none,</hi> doth make the Perſon of the Father; the very ſelf-ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>in Number,</hi> with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty <hi>to be of the Father,</hi> maketh the Perſon of the Son; the ſame Subſtance having added to it the property of <hi>proceeding from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two,</hi> maketh the Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt: So that in every Perſon there is implied both <hi>the Subſtance</hi> of God, which is one, and alſo that Property which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſame Perſon [that is to ſay, the Divine Subſtance with one of the three Properties before ſaid, as ſuppoſe the Property <hi>to be of none</hi>] really and truly to differ from the other two.</q> That is, to differ from the Divine Subſtance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under the Properties <hi>to be of the Father,</hi> and <hi>to proceed from the Father and Son.</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> then, as well as Dr. <hi>S</hi>—<hi>th,</hi> underſtood the Doctrine of the Schools and Church concerning the Trinity, to be this. That there is but one infinite intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Divine Subſtance <hi>in Number,</hi> which Subſtance is the Subject (if we may ſo ſpeak) of ſundry Divine Attributes, ſuch as Omnipotence, perfect Goodneſs, conſummate Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and the reſt: none of which Attributes is more than once in the Divine Subſtance or Godhead; there is in God but one Omniſcience, one Omnipotence, one Holineſs, one Goodneſs in number; as the Nature or Subſtance is but one in number, ſo each Attribute is but once (not thrice) in the Nature, or Godhead. But then beſides theſe <hi>Attributes,</hi> there are alſo three <hi>Perſons</hi> in God; not <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſons,</hi> for that would plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make three Beings, three Spirits, and three Gods; but three ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as in very Deed are but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Properties, or Modes, or if you will give them any the like Name. Such Properties as Grammarians and Claſſical Authors (and after them, Metaphyſicians) call Perſons: for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them, a Father is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a Son is a Perſon, a Sanctifier is a Perſon; and whoſoever ſuſtains theſe three Relations (or any other the like) is by them called three Perſons. Thus, for example, <hi>M. Tullius,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges in every Man no leſs than four Perſons; namely, firſt, <hi>The ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Nature,</hi> by which we differ from Brutes; next, the <hi>particular Properties</hi> (of Body and Mind) which diſtinguiſh one rational Nature (or Man) from another; thirdly, the circumſtance, or <hi>manner of Life</hi> of each Man, as that he is a Rich Man or a Poor; laſtly, <hi>The Profeſſion</hi> that any one takes up, as to be a Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, a Profeſſor in Philoſophy, a Pleader, a Poet, or Writer to the Stage. <hi>De Officiis; l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30, 32. A Perſon then in grammatical, <hi>criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſpeaking,</hi> is not a <hi>ſubſiſting Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but ſome either (characteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46702:7"/>Property, or ſome Relation, or State, of a ſubſiſting intellectual Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: and it is of Perſons, <hi>critically ſo called,</hi> that the Church would be underſtood, when ſhe ſays, there are three Perſons in God; ſhe doth not mean <hi>three ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are called Perſons, becauſe they are ſo many intellectual Beings. Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> very well underſtood the Doctrine of the Schools, when he notes; that the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are three <hi>relative Subſiſtences,</hi> but ſo (ſaith he) that their <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence</hi> is nothing elſe but their <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> that is, they are <hi>meer States, Modes,</hi> or <hi>Relations, which (in a ſenſe) ſubſiſt in the Divine Subſtance, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Godhead.</hi> Which indeed is to ſay, God is three Perſons, as any particular Man, may be three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for the ſame Man may be a Father, a Son, and may proceed from two others; namely, from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother. And though this is not the very manner of God's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three Perſons; yet the ternary Perſonality in God is ſounded on the ſame Notion and Conception of the word Perſons: and that Conception no more deſtroys his real Unity, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a Being, as a Spirit, or as God, than that three-fold Perſonali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a Man, makes him to be more than one Man, or than one <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon.</hi> The ſhort is, according to theſe Gentlemen, God is but one <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> (or real Perſon: but this one (phyſical) Perſon having three (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal) Relations, is thereby three <hi>relative Perſons;</hi> three ſuch Perſons as one Man (or one Angel) who hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to have three Relations, is. The three <hi>relative Perſons</hi> no more contradict the Unity of God, than the theeefold Relation of <hi>Solomon,</hi> namely, as <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> as <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and as <hi>proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> from <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts his being but one Man, or one <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> and <hi>phyſical</hi> Perſon.</p>
               <p>It is well known, what Judgment the <hi>Real <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> make of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Trinity. Mr. <hi>How</hi> (becauſe he delights to be civil) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelf to ſay; the Real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians will judg, it is not Senſe; <hi>View of the Conſiderations,</hi> pag. 50. The Biſhop of <hi>Gloc.</hi> thinks it can have little better Succeſs, than only to make ſport for the <hi>Socinians;</hi> ſo he concludes his 28 <hi>Propoſitions</hi> in his 2d <hi>Defence</hi> of them. But Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> cries, <hi>'tis the Philoſophy of</hi> Gotham. Nay, Mr. <hi>How</hi> himſelf, though out of regard to ſo great a Party as the Nominal Trinitarians are, he will only ſay of their Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>'tis not Senſe;</hi> yet he reckons <hi>P. Lombard,</hi> the ſuppoſed Parent of this Explication of the Trinity, <hi>one of the four Evangeliſts of Anti-Chriſt.</hi> Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> alſo, and the Learned Author (Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi>) of the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>S—th's</hi> Animadverſions on Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> ſay a great many bitter things of the Divines of the Schools, by occaſion of this (ſenſeleſs) Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Trinity. Theſe Gentlemen cannot bear it, that the ſame <hi>intellectual Subſtance</hi> in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which is but only to ſay <hi>the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46702:7"/>ſame numerical Perſon,</hi> ſhould be made to be three Perſons, becauſe of three (pretended) internal Relations, or <hi>a threefold Relation to himſelf,</hi> which he is (abſurdly) feigned to ſuſtain. They confeſs, that the ſame intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Subſtance, or <hi>ſubſiſting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> may be <hi>a Father,</hi> and <hi>Son,</hi> and may <hi>proceed</hi> from another, or others: but then theſe muſt be <hi>external,</hi> not <hi>internal</hi> Relations; that is, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Father and Son to himſelf, as is implied in the Scholaſtick Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, becauſe it ſuppoſes this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Proceeder, are really but one <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> (or phyſical) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though they are three (and may be 300) Critical or <hi>Metaphyſical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> If the Schools and Nominals ſaid, God is three Perſons, becauſe of three <hi>external Relations,</hi> that is, three Relations to his Creatures: this might be underſtood, becauſe the ſame Man may have three Relations to others, and is (on that account) called by <hi>Claſſical Writers</hi> three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, though <hi>now,</hi> and <hi>in the Engliſh Tongue</hi> that Senſe of the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> is quite out of Uſe. But to talk of three <hi>internal Relations,</hi> or that the ſame intellectual Subſtance (which is to ſay, the ſame ſubſiſting or <hi>phyſical Perſon</hi>) is Unbegotten, and Begotten, is <hi>of none,</hi> and yet <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from two;</hi> to make him a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a Son, when there is none but himſelf to whom he is either way ſo related: it is ſuch pitious Trifling, as utterly deſtroys the Patience of the <hi>Realiſts</hi> that hear it; while others think that the Philoſopher, who is ſaid never to have laughed but once, might even have done it a ſecond Time on this ocaſion. In very Deed, our Brother <hi>S—th</hi> has need of all his Talents and Helps, his Leiſure, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Wit, Courage, the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and all the <hi>Moderns,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him againſt the inſults of the Realiſts; who have here ſo manifeſt an Advantage, and are (for the moſt part) Men ſo able to take and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it, that he will find at length, he has no way to reſcue his Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or himſelf, but by Recrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; that is, by ſhewing the as great Abſurdity, and plain Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the Explication of the Trinity b the Realiſts.</p>
               <p>It may be worth while to inquire here, whether the Nominals do not know, or are not aware, that in very deed they are Unitarians, or (as ſome call us) Socinians? I am of Opinion they are ſenſible of it, and I ground my ſelf on the expreſs words of ſome of them, and thoſe too the moſt eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: For example, Dr. <hi>J. Wallis,</hi> and Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> intimate plainly enough; that the Socinian Doctrine and theirs, is the ſame. Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> anſwering to a Socinian, in his 3d Letter or <hi>Vindication of the Athanaſian Creed,</hi> p. 62, 63. has theſe words. <q rend="inline">That which makes theſe Expreſſions [he means the Terms uſed by Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians, eſpecially this, <hi>God is three Perſons</hi> or <hi>three Perſons are one God]</hi> ſeem harſh to <hi>the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> is, becauſe they have uſed themſelves to fancy that Notion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> according to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46702:8"/>which <hi>three Men</hi> are accounted to be <hi>three Perſons,</hi> and theſe three Perſons to be three Men. But they may conſider there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> and in common uſe too, wherein <hi>the ſame Man</hi> may be ſaid to ſuſtain <hi>divers Perſons,</hi> and thoſe Perſons to be the ſame Man, that is, the ſame Man ſuſtaining divers Capacities. And then it will ſeem no more harſh to ſay, the three Perſons, Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, are one God; than to ſay, God the Creator, God the Redeemer, and God the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, is one God: which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, even <hi>to this Anſwerer</hi> [he means the Socinian, to whom he is there anſwering] would not ſeem <hi>harſh,</hi> or be thought <hi>nonſenſe.</hi>
                  </q> Here he ſaith theſe two things; 1. That <hi>three Perſons</hi> when affirmed of God, are not to be taken as when we ſay, <hi>three Men</hi> are <hi>three Perſons;</hi> but in that ſenſe, wherein the <hi>ſame Man</hi> is commonly (he means by Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Claſſical Authors) called three Perſons, becauſe he hath three Capacities; as (ſuppoſe) of a King, an Husband, and a Father. This is the Senſe, in which God is ſaid to be a Trinity, or three Perſons: he hath theſe three Capacities, of Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier; and in that regard (or ſenſe) is ſaid to be three Perſons. 2. That to a Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, this account not only will not be <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> but not ſo much as <hi>harſh</hi> or uncouth. No one can deny, that the Doctor well perceived, that the Socinian Doctrine and his were indeed the ſame: a Sicinian, he ſays, would not be offended at this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of a Trinity of <hi>Perſons;</hi> Perſon here not being intended for <hi>a ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> as a particular Man is, but for <hi>a Capacity</hi> only of a really ſubſiſting Perſon. And whereas the Socinian Author of <hi>the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Explications of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had ſaid;</hi> if Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and the Nominal Party believe but one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance in Number, which hath one only Underſtanding, one Will, one Energy or power of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Number, he is a Socinian or Unitarian; for in very Deed, this is but one (really) <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon:</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> nothing abaſh'd, with his uſual dexterity and preſence of Mind, anſwers to this effect; That <q rend="inline">ſo he believes, and ſo the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, and that 'tis a good hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Socinians are come over to him, and to the Church, or <hi>fal in with him, and the Church.</hi>
                  </q> I cannot at preſent find the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar page of <hi>Tritheiſm charged,</hi> where this is ſaid, not having made a mark againſt thoſe Lines; but I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well, that I report rightly the Senſe of the Paſſage. His words need no Comment, they are a plain acknowledgment that (by that way of expreſſing themſelves) the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians fall in with the Church, and with him. But whereas he ſaith, they fall in with the Church, as the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians are content, that in Honour to the Church it be ſo ſaid: ſo <hi>the Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> (or as they call
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46702:8"/>us, Socinians) claim it as their right; to be owned the firſt Diſcoveres, that all the Heats between the Church and the Socinians, have aroſe from this only, this they miſtook one anothers true meaning, by occaſion of the canting un-ſcriptural Terms, <hi>Trinity, Perſons</hi> (and ſuch like) uſed by the Church.</p>
               <p>For it is moſt true, that tho for Peace-ſake we ſubmit to the Language of the Church, as 'tis interpreted bby the Nominals; yet the Church's Terms are very improper: for the ſame ſingle numerical <hi>ſubſiſting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (as the Church and the Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans believe God to be) is not <hi>now</hi> in any Language called three Perſons, by occaſion of three Relations, Modes, or Properties adhering to him; tho 'tis confeſſed, the (Roman) Claſſical Authors ſo ſpake.</p>
               <p>But whereas the Nominals, or the Church, ſince the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> that they may ſeem not to have departed from the Fathers, ſtill talk of <hi>Trinity,</hi> Paternity, Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Proceſſion, Hypoſtatical Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Father, Son, and Spirit; on which (as we have ſeen) they put ſuch a meaning, even thoſe of them that ſpeak moſt Harſhly and Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, as no ways deſtroys the Unity of God, or that he is but one <hi>phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical</hi> and <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon;</hi> and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Realiſts</hi> inſult them, as Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that know not, or at beſt heed not what they ſay: the Socinians think 'tis even neceſſary, nay, a due Juſtice, to have more regard and reſpect for theſe their weak Brethren. Firſt, We conſider; that after all the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper</hi> Terms, <hi>impertinent</hi> Language, and <hi>unſignificant,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>dangerous</hi> Words, uſed by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals; all the Denominations of them agree at length, in this Sound and Orthodox Explication and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that there is but one Divine intellectual Subſtance, but one infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spirit, but one <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon</hi> of God. Secondly, The Nominals chooſe indeed to ſpeak (almoſt, a Realiſt would ſay altogether) <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſically,</hi> and to retain the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Tritheiſtical Terms</hi> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. but this was, that they might reſtore the true Faith and genuine Chriſtianity, without Noiſe and Tumult: the School-Divines, and Council at <hi>Lateran,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the corrupted Doctrine of the Church, by only interpreting (ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and dextrouſly) the Language and Terms, which their Tritheiſtick Predeceſſors had brought into the Church, into her very Liturgies, and Creeds.—So many Councils, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fathers, and from them ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations had affirmed a Trinity of Divine Perſons; that to oppoſe this Doctrine, would have begot endleſs Striſes, bitter Contentions and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions: and after all, probably the Reformers would have come off no better than the Socinians have done; that is, with all the clear Truth they have of their ſide, and all their Dexterity and Wit in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging it, being over-powered by the numbers of the contrary Herd, they ſhould have been anſwered with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46702:9"/>Penal Laws, and Sanguinary Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of the thoſe Laws. They took therefore a Courſe that would do their Buſineſs, unperceived by the moſt; and when perceived by ſome few, it would not be hard to convict them of Tritheiſm, and explode them as Tritheiſts; and ſo <hi>de facto</hi> they ſerved <hi>Abbat Joachim.</hi> And then getting their Explication (of the Trinity) confirmed by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran,</hi> they happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored the publick Profeſſion (and Faith) of the Unity of God, by an Authority which none dares to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict: for a General Council (as was before noted) is the higheſt Court of the Church; that laſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal (on Earth) from which there lies no Appeal.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Noetians</hi> and <hi>Sabellians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THERE is yet another Branch of Nominal Trinitarians, more antient far than thoſe yet mentioned; for about the Year of Chriſt 200, the <hi>Noetians,</hi> and but a little after them the <hi>Sabellians</hi> aroſe: both theſe ſaid, there is but one Divine <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Eſſence</hi> or <hi>Nature;</hi> and as the Subſtance of the Father, Son and Spiirt, is numerically One, ſo conſequently (ſaid they) there is but <hi>one Perſon</hi> of God; Father, Son and Spirit, are but only <hi>three Names</hi> of God, given to him in Scripture, by occaſion of ſo many ſeveral Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations towards the Creature. For in regard of the Creation, God is called the <hi>Father:</hi> he is named the <hi>Son,</hi> as he wrought Miracles and accompliſhed the whole Work of Man's Redemption, by the Lord Chriſt, in whom he dwelt after a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar and extraordinary manner; and who indeed was the Son of God, by miraculous Conception in the Womb of Holy <hi>Mary:</hi> He has the Name of the Holy Ghoſt or <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> from his omnipotent Energy or Power, by which he effecteth all things. In a word, the <hi>Noetians</hi> and <hi>Sabellians</hi> held, that God is <hi>but one ſubſisting Perſon;</hi> yet that with reſpect to things without Him, he may be called (as the Modern Nominals now ſpeak) <hi>three Relative Perſons:</hi> the one <hi>ſubſisting</hi> Perſon of God ſuſtaineth the <hi>three Names</hi> of Father, Son and Spirit; which being the Relations of God towards things without him, he is ſo many <hi>Relative Perſons,</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> in a Claſſical cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Senſe.</p>
               <p>And this too is the Explication of the Trinity, by that Party in the firſt <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> who contrived the word <hi>Homo-uſios,</hi> or <hi>Conſubſtantial;</hi> by which they meant, that the three Divine Perſons have all <hi>the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:</hi> and this is the Party, which after the breaking up of that famous Council, and upon the ſudden Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence of the Arian Faction, were
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46702:9"/>perſecuted by the Arians; and were conſidered by all others as the true <hi>Nicene Party,</hi> till about the Year of Chriſt 380, the <hi>Realiſts</hi> obtained that it ſhould be ſaid, that God is <hi>tres Hypoſtaſes, three ſubſisting Perſons.</hi> Indeed there are ſeveral Comma's in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, very hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable to the <hi>Sabellian</hi> Doctrine: but as there were three powerful, and almoſt equal Parties in the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Council, the Arian Party, the Realiſts, and the Sabellians; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thought it enough, if they could procure <hi>Homo-uſios</hi> (conſubſtantial) to be inſerted into the Creed. For that ambiguous Word may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted in favour of all thoſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. It may be interpreted <hi>the ſame Subſtance,</hi> the <hi>very ſame,</hi> or ſame in Number, and ſo it eſtabliſhes the Sabellian Doctrine; or <hi>the ſame in Kind and all Properties,</hi> and ſo it countenances the <hi>Realiſts;</hi> or it may be underſtood <hi>of like Subſtance,</hi> and ſo it pleaſes the <hi>Ariani molles,</hi> the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Arians:</hi> tho the rigid Arians in the Council would by no means admit of it; they rather choſe to loſe their Biſhopricks. But when the Council was broke up, it was perceived by the other Parties, that the zealous Aſſertors of <hi>Homo-uſios (of the ſame Subſtance)</hi> were all of them Sabellians; believed that God is but one <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> and therefore <hi>deſtroyed the real Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of the Son,</hi> whom the Arians as well as the Realiſts took to be <hi>a ſubſisting Perſon,</hi> not a <hi>relative Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> a <hi>Reſpect</hi> or a <hi>Name</hi> only. And as the Arians diſcovered, that the <hi>Homo-uſians</hi> were indeed Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; ſo theſe latter charged the Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Realiſts as guilty of a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Tritheiſm, becauſe they ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>Homo-uſios,</hi> as to make Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Spirit, to be diſtinct, intellectual <hi>Subſtances,</hi> or <hi>ſubſisting Perſons.</hi> Let us hear their own Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, <hi>Socrates,</hi> L. 1. c. 23. <q rend="inline">Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Council, the Biſhops wrangled about the word <hi>Homo-uſios.</hi> Thoſe that were for it, were cenſured by the contrary Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as <hi>Sabellians;</hi> and were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Impious,</hi> becauſe <hi>they deſtroyed the real Exiſtence of the Son.</hi> Thoſe that were againſt it, were condemned by ſuch as were for it, as reviving Gentiliſm, or <hi>the belief of more Gods.</hi>
                  </q> And this Truth, that Sabellianiſm was then taken to be the <hi>Nicene</hi> Doctrine, or the ſame with <hi>the Doctrine of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality,</hi> is owned by the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Critick <hi>H. Valeſius,</hi> in his Notes on <hi>Sacrates,</hi> L. 1. c. 24. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Hiſtorian ſaith, That <hi>Cyrus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Berea</hi> was depoſed, <hi>for holding the Sabellian Doctrine: Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius</hi> notes hereupon, in theſe words; <hi>that is, for the Doctrine of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality,</hi> or the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, which Council brought in the <hi>Homo-uſiotes,</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:46702:10"/>
               <head>The Sum of what has been ſaid, concerning the <hi>Nominals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THESE at length are the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Nominals.</hi> They all agree, that the three Perſons of God are not <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons;</hi> they are not ſo many diſtinct Lives, Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, Wills, or Energies, which (together with a particular Subſtance) make <hi>a ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> and if they are <hi>more than one,</hi> they make <hi>ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> phyſical real or ſubſiſting Perſons: no, they are Perſons in a quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Senſe, from that vulgar accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word <hi>Perſons.</hi> They are either <hi>three Attributes</hi> of God; Goodneſs, Wiſdom, and Power. Or <hi>three external Acts;</hi> Creation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and Sanctification. Or <hi>two internal Acts</hi> of the <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon</hi> of the Father; that is to ſay, the Father <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> himſelf and his own Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Or <hi>three internal Relations;</hi> that is, three Relations of God to himſelf: namely, the Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or Godhead, conſidered as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten, and Proceeding. Or <hi>three Names</hi> of God, aſcribed to him by the Holy Scriptures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is <hi>the Father</hi> of all things, by Creation; and becauſe he did In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit and Operate (after an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and miraculous manner) in the Perſon of the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who was verily <hi>the Son</hi> of God by his wonderful manner of Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and (laſt of all) becauſe he ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth all things (more eſpecially, our Sanctification) by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is to ſay; his Energy or Power.</p>
               <p>Every one ſees, theſe are very crude Conceits to be dignified with the Name of <hi>Myſteries:</hi> but withal the Reader is to know, that the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> is ſtill behind. For the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lies not here, that <hi>one ſubſiſting Perſon</hi> is made to be <hi>three Relative Perſons,</hi> or three <hi>Names,</hi> or three <hi>Attributes;</hi> or that God is called <hi>Father</hi> becauſe he Created all things, <hi>Son</hi> becauſe he Inhabited and Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Son our Lord Chriſt, or <hi>Spirit</hi> becauſe he is that Almighty Energy which effected all things: for all this, though very harſh and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, is yet intelligible; and the manner of ſpeaking in Antient Times, did warrant ſuch ways of expreſſing themſelves, as may be ſeen in the Claſſical Authors, both Romans and Greeks. But it is Myſtery, becauſe (or, as) when you apply any of theſe Explications of the Trinity, to the Incarnation, the Hypoſtatical Union, or the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; 'tis next to impoſſible, to make any degree of Senſe of it: for how can we ſay that <hi>an Attribute,</hi> or <hi>a Property,</hi> or <hi>a Name,</hi> or <hi>to be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,</hi> or any ſuch like was <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> or <hi>Satisfied</hi> for Sin? as alſo becauſe the Terms <hi>Generation</hi> and <hi>Proceſſion</hi> cannot, without moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46702:10"/>and ridiculous Subtleties, be applied to three Attributes; or to Underſtanding, and Willing ones ſelf; or to the ſame Unbegotten, and unproceeding Subſtance; or to Creation and Redemption and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification. In ſhort, our poor Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Nominals are here purely conſtrained and forced to call their Doctrine <hi>Myſtery;</hi> becauſe 'tis ſo hard to find a way, to reconcile it to the ordinary Forms of ſpeaking, <hi>that is, to common Senſe.</hi> Therefore here the Realiſts glory over them; here they have an ample Field, for Wit and Sarcaſm to parade in: here they ask the Nominals an hundred male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent pleaſant Queſtions; to which they anſwer, by objecting Profaneſs to the Queſtioniſts, and by the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous word Myſtery. Moreover they (the Nominals) comfort themſelves, that the whole Myſtery (or Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity) of their Doctrine, conſiſts <hi>only in the Terms</hi> [<hi>Trinity,</hi> &amp;c.] which they are forced to retain, to preſerve the Church's Peace; <hi>not in the Senſe,</hi> or <hi>thing intended:</hi> for the meaning and Sum of their Doctrine, as they explain it, is; there is but one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon;</hi> not more ſuch Perſons, for that were to ſay <hi>more Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, after all the dry Bobs of the Realiſts, on the Nominals; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves muſt take their turn of being jeered. For when their Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come to be examined; and their Contradictions to, and Comdemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of one another as Tritheiſts, are conſidered: the Nominals will ſeem to be profound Philoſophers, deep Sages, in compariſon with theſe their Oppoſers; and theſe Oppoſers (the Realiſts) ſuch awkward, uncouth Ruſticks, that a great deal of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or Diſcretion muſt be uſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ones ſelf, to be civil to them. But I ſhall not conſider their Perſons or Doctrine, as the Nominals do; neither with Railery, nor Anger, as the manner now is: but only as deſirous to convince them, that they have as cauſleſly departed from the Doctrine of the Church, as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Realiſts:</hi> that they are divided, into two Factions; which comdemn each the other, of manifeſt Tritheiſm.</head>
               <p>THE firſt Obſervation, to be made on the Real Trinitarians, is; not only that (as has been ſaid) they ſtand Condemned and Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd as Hereticks, by a General Council, and by all the Moderns, who are more, and more Learned than the Fathers; or that they are every day challeng'd and impeached of Tritheiſm, by Learned Men of the Nominal Party, and Appeals made to Univerſities, and the Divinity-Chairs, againſt them: But <q rend="inline">they themſelves being divided among
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46702:11"/>themſelves, cenſure one another as manifeſt Tritheiſts.</q> They are divided into many Parties, but all thoſe Parties are again bandied into two principal Factions; that can never be reconciled to one another.</p>
               <p>One of theſe Factions ſaith, that <hi>the three Divine Perſons are every way equal:</hi> namely, Co-eternal, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Omnipotent, Omniſcient, and Omnipreſent. Moſt of the Fathers, after the Year 380, were of this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion: becauſe they plainly ſaw, that to aſcribe any Perfection, or degree of that Perfection, to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more than to the Son or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is to ſay in effect; that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only is true God, not the Son or Spirit, becauſe whoſoever hath not omnimodous Perfection, cannot be God. And for this reaſon, they affirm, and earneſtly contend; That <q rend="inline"> any one of the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is equal to all the Three; the whole Trinity is not greater, or more perfectly God, than any one of the Trinity is.</q> Surely a ſtrange Paradox, that one Third ſhould be Equal, or Equivalent to the Whole. Yet the Modern Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, <hi>the moſt</hi> hold this Opinion, as well as th Antients did.</p>
               <p>But the more Learned and Ableſt of the Moderns, deteſt ſo much as the Mention of three Equal Divine Perſons: for what are three Gods, ſay they, of three equally Superemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and All-ſufficient <hi>(ſubſiſting)</hi> Perſons are not three Gods? If they are Equal in Dignity and Power, as wel as Co-eternal; we can poſſibly have no other Notion of three Gods, but three ſuch Perſons. Therefore theſe Gentlemen ſuppoſe, that the Son and Spirit are inferiour to the Father in all things; but only this, that they are Co-eternal with him: they are Subordinate to him, Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on him; and are Omnipotent (and the reſt of the Divine Attributes) not <hi>ad intra,</hi> or of themſelves, but only <hi>as he concurs with them to all their Actions. Epiſcopius</hi> (Inſtit. l. 4. c. 32.) and Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> (<hi>Intellec. Syſtem,</hi> pag. 603, 604.) largely defend this Opinion; and condemn thoſe of undeniable Tritheiſm, who make the Son and Spirit to be equal to the Father. But to know the Writers, who believe the equality of the Son and Spirit with the Father, from thoſe that deny it; this Rule moſt commonly will ſerve. They that ſay the Son is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(God of himſelf, and Independent)</hi> generally hold the abſolute Equality of all the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and that one Perſon of the Trinity, is equal to the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: for if he were not, they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſee, he could not be <hi>perfect God;</hi> for ſomething would be wanting to him, that is found in the whole Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. But thoſe that deny <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, do (more commonly) make the Son and Spirit ſubordinate to the Father; not only in Dignity, but in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reſpects: but theſe, though they ground themſelves on the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nicene Creed (which in direct oppoſition to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>God of himſelf,</hi> affirms, the Son is <hi>God of God,</hi> that is, God <hi>of,</hi> or <hi>from</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46702:11"/>the Father) ſeldom care to ſpeak plain, that they may avoid giving Offence.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider the Arguments, with which theſe two Factions of Realiſts attack one another: and what effectual uſe <hi>the Nominals</hi> make of thoſe very Arguments, to ridicule and deſtroy both Parties, and their common Principle or Foundation, namely this; that the Divine Perſons are <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> not Perſons, but only critically ſo called.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>By what Arguments the Parties of <hi>Realiſts,</hi> attack and oppoſe each the other; and what (effectual) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, the <hi>Nominals</hi> make of this Contention.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIRST,</hi> ſay they who affirm the Equality; if the Son and Spirit are Subordinate in Dignity and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and inferior in Power and other Divine Attributes: it ſeems ſelf-evident, that either the Father only muſt be ſaid to the truly God, becauſe he only hath omnimodous Perfection, and in the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; or that there is <hi>one Great God,</hi> and <hi>two Inferior</hi> or leſſer ones. To this, they that maintain the Inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the three Perſons, anſwer; by retorting the Argument, thus: If the Divine Perſons are equal, then there are <hi>three Omnipotents,</hi> and <hi>three Omniſcients;</hi> which is the very No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of three Gods, and is denied <hi>in terminis</hi> (or expreſly) by the Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſian Creed, which ſaith, <hi>not three Almighties, but one Almighty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But was it ever heard, ſince the Creation of things, ſay (the common Enemy to both) <hi>the Nominals;</hi> that two contending erroneous Parties, did more effectually ruin one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's common Miſtake? For as 'tis ſelf-evident on the one Hand, that it being the very Definition of God (the Notion that all Men have of him) that he is a Being Omnimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douſly (or abſolutely) Perfect; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Son or Spirit want ſome Perfections, or ſome degree of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, neither of them can be God, but the Father only: So on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, 'tis noleſs inconteſtable: that three Diſtinct, and (really) <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſons,</hi> each of which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes all Perfections, and every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of thoſe Perfections, muſt (of neceſſity) be three Gods. Why do not theſe unhappy Men, ſay the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, ſee; that three Almighties, and three Omniſcients, are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly three Gods: and that on the contrary, if only one of them is (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally and verily) Almighty, as well as Superiour in Dignity to the other two; he only is true God, they are Gods <hi>only by Courteſy and Civility of Speech?</hi> Do not the two contrary Arguments of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky Reaſoners, make a Dilemma;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46702:12"/>that overthrows their common Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, even this, that the Perſons of the Trinity are <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons?</hi> Have they not ſhown us, how to argue ſuccesfully againſt them both; for we learn from themſelves, to ſay: either the (imagined,) <hi>ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons</hi> of their Trinity are equal, or not equal; if equal, they muſt be three Gods, <hi>becauſe nothing is wanting to any of them toward making him a perfect God;</hi> if unequal, only one of them is properly and truly God, the other two by Civility and Courteſy only; they may be Gods to thoſe that have a mind to compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but wanting ſome Perfections, or ſome Degrees of Perfection, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them can be God in a The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ological or Philoſophical Senſe. But the Pleaſure and Sport of the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals increaſes, when the Realiſts ſeek to extricate themſelves from theſe Noozes. For example.</p>
               <p>The Realiſts that are for the Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſay; Father, Son, and Spirit, though omnimodouſly Perfect (and ſubſiſting) Perſons, are one God, <hi>by their mutual Concord and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> So alſo <hi>Origen,</hi> and other Antenicenes, make out the Unity of God in a Ternary of Perſons; tho they did not believe the Equality. To this, the Nominals anſwer; the (ſuppoſed) Divine <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons</hi> are hereby <hi>loving Friends;</hi> which is a good Hearing, for ſhould three <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties</hi> fall out, what would the World do? but if they are not only <hi>diſtinct,</hi> but <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſons, they are as much <hi>three Gods, in a proper and natural Senſe,</hi> as if they were never ſo much <hi>at odds;</hi> Concord doth not make a Real or Phyſical Unity, which is the Unity of God, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Moral <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or ſuch as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Friends</hi> or <hi>Allies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other Realiſts, almoſt all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derns, ſee, and confeſs this; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſay, their Gods are one; <hi>becauſe they are in one another.</hi> But ſay the Nominals, God is in his Creatures, more eſpecially in the Faithful, and they in him; as our Saviour himſelf witneſſes: are they thereby all but one God? is the Creature deified by being in God, and he in us?</p>
               <p>No, no, ſay others; but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons who are thus <hi>in</hi> one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>have like Subſtances, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and Properties:</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid of God and the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Admirable again, cry the Nominals; but remove this one Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. If theſe <hi>reſembling Gods,</hi> are ſo united in their Subſtances, or ſo <hi>in</hi> one another; that their Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are <hi>continuous,</hi> like the Parts of the ſame Angel, or like the (aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable) Parts of the ſame Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 'tis plain that by ſuch an Union (or mutual Immeation) of their Parts, they are become but one (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting) Perſon in number, which is what the Nominals and Socinians contend for: but if they are only ſo united, or ſo <hi>in</hi> one another, that their Parts are only <hi>Contiguous,</hi> like Wine and Oil ſhook together, and yet never incorporating; this is but only Contact and <hi>Juxta-poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46702:12"/>and doth not make the three Perſons to be one, much leſs one God, any more than all the Men <hi>in a cloſe Croud</hi> are one Man, or than the Wine and Oil (before-ſaid) are one Subſtance. In a word, ſay the Nominals, who ſees not; that the three Divine <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſons, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>like Subſtances</hi> or Properties, or what is all one, <hi>like Natures,</hi> are but only <hi>Gods reſembling one another?</hi> and whether they be <hi>in</hi> at <hi>out</hi> of one another, <hi>likes are never the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis well; but it may be, they have better luck, who ſay the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons are not equal; but the Second and Third are ſubordinate in Authority, and inferiour in their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The Objection. againſt them, is; that hereby, either the ſecond and third Perſons, are neither of them God, but only the Firſt: or here is one great God, and two leſſer. They reply, that as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his two Sons, are one Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Family; though the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power is in the Father, and only ſecondarily derivatively, and leſs abſolutely in the Sons: So Father, Son, and H. Spirit are one God, becauſe the two latter (though ſubject and inferior to the former) have like Authority and Power with him, <hi>for that he always concurs with them.</hi> But the Nominals cry; this is not one God, in a Phyſical or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Senſe, but only in a Political: and that the (ſuppoſed) Father of the Family and his two Sons, may as well be ſaid to be <hi>one Man;</hi> as <hi>one Maſter,</hi> For in very Deed, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Father is Maſter; though he delegates Authority and Power to his Children, during his Pleaſue: or if Power and Authority is abſolutely and irrevocably conferred on them, they are as much Maſters as he; and there is no longer one Maſter, but three.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another Argument of. thoſe that contend for the Equality, is; if the Son and Spirit are unequal to the Father, and he only hath omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious Perfection, with all degrees of thoſe Perfections: then <hi>the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are very unneceſſarily ſuperadded to the latter;</hi> he is perfect God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, they add nothing to him; we can underſtand <hi>them</hi> but only <hi>as Foils</hi> to ſet off, and to recommend. his Perfections.</p>
               <p>This Reaſoning alſo is retorted, by them that hold the inequality of the Perſons in the (ſuppoſed) Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for they reply; if there are three equally perfect (Divine) <hi>ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Perſons,</hi> two of them are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant, or <hi>more than needs.</hi> If we ſuppoſe them, ſay theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, unequal, we leave but one God; becauſe the Second and Third are God but only as they are united to the Firſt, by <hi>his</hi> Concurrence with them, and by <hi>their</hi> Subordination and Subjection to him: but if we ſay, they are equal; here are two unneceſſary Perſons ſuppoſed not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any cauſe for it, for any one of theſe <hi>abſolutely perfect Perſons</hi> is ſufficient for himſelf, and for the Creation; but the Unity alſo of God, the firſt and moſt important
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46702:13"/>Article of <hi>Revealed Religion,</hi> is loſt, becauſe it cannot be imagined, but That <q rend="inline">three <hi>(ſubſiſting)</hi> abſolutely perfect Perſons muſt be <hi>as</hi> truly three Gods, <hi>as</hi> one ſuch Perſon (which no Body will deny) is one God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here again the Nominals ſee, and take their Advantage: 'tis well, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well argued, Gentlemen, ſay they, on both ſides. For 'tis ſo true, as not to be queſtioned; that if the <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons</hi> which you have imagined, are unequal, and only one of them is <hi>All-ſufficient,</hi> for himſelf, and for the Creation: the two <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Perſons</hi> are but dead <hi>Weights;</hi> of no uſe, but only that the other may be the better pleaſed at his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, when compared with their Littleneſs. And 'tis true again, what the other Party ſays; that of three ſubſiſting <hi>All-ſufficient</hi> Perſons, two are not only redundant, but take away the Unity of God: for if 'tis true, that one ſuch Perſon is a perfect God, three of them (for that very Reaſon) muſt be three perfect Gods. Why do you not perceive, ſay the Nominals to the Realiſts, that your own Arguments deſtroy your Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis? one <hi>perfect</hi> Perſon and two <hi>imperfect</hi> Perſons are indeed one God, but the whole God-head then is in the <hi>perfect</hi> Perſon, as We and the Socinians contend: and three (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting) abſolutely perfect Perſons are a Trinity, not only of Perſons, but (becauſe each of them is abſolutely Perfect) of Gods. O ſtrange Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertence, ſay theſe Gentlemen! that Men ſhould not ſee, that one perfect Perſon is alone a (moſt) compleat God, and is not helped to be more ſo, by the addition of two Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: and that three perfect (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting) Perſons either are three Gods, or one cannot be one God; but <hi>one perfect Perſon</hi> is the very Definition of God, dictated to us by Natural Light.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Say they that hold the Equality of the Perſons. If the ſecond and third Perſons are inferiour in Power, and other Divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and Subordinate in Dignity and Authority; they muſt be <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely</hi> Inferiour, and <hi>infinitely</hi> Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate; for whatſoever is ſhort of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Perfection, is infinitely ſhort of it: for if a Perfection is not Infinite, 'tis but only Finite, which is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhort of Infinite; as all both Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Divines agree. Let us apply <hi>this,</hi> to the (ſuppoſed) <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> Divine Perſons: if the Second and Third are <hi>leſs Perfect</hi> than the Firſt, they are (for that Reaſon) but finitely Perfect, and conſequently are infinitely ſhort of the Perfection of the Firſt. But will you ſay, in the hearing of ſober and deſcerning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; that a finite Perfection or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is God ? <hi>God,</hi> ſay the Party that hold the Inequality; but if it is ſo certain (as you take it to be) that two leſs perfect Beings can neither of them be God, but only an abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfect Perſon: it will follow however, from this very Reaſoning, that three perfect Perſons are three Gods. Becauſe for that very Cauſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46702:13"/>why you affirm, that of two leſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Perſons, neither of them can be God; you muſt ſay, three perfect Perſons are three Gods: for the weight of your Argument, laying in this Suppoſition, That <q rend="inline">only a perfect Perſon, and every ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is a perfect God;</q> you muſt either give up <hi>that,</hi> or own that your whole Reaſoning is Impertinent and Null.</p>
               <p>The Nominals turn alſo this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certation againſt the common Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis of both theſe Parties of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts. How well, ſay they, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is it argued by the former; that Perſons leſs than abſolutely Perfect, are (of neceſſity) but finitely Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, and conſequently cannot be Gods, or God? and 'tis as ſoundly urged; that if <hi>this</hi> be a good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, if imperfect Perſons cannot be Gods or God, and a perfect Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, then three or more perfect Perſons muſt be more Gods: becauſe <q rend="inline"> as Imperfection or leſs Perfection denies God-head; ſo the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modous abſolute Perfection of Perſons, muſt make ſo many Gods as there are <hi>ſuch</hi> Perſons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But hitherto of the firſt Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the Realiſts; that the two grand Factions of them, and which include all their leſſer Parties, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn one another of Tritheiſm: and that the Church, or Nominal Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians, turn the Arguments of the contending Parties of Realiſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them and the Principle for which they ſtrive; namely, That the Perſons of the Trinity are <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſons;</hi> when indeed 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God that <hi>really ſubſiſts,</hi> the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of the Godhead are only Perſons <hi>critically ſo called,</hi> that is, they are only <hi>Relative Subſiſtences,</hi> they are but only the internal Relations of God to himſelf, or his external (threefold) Relation to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That the <hi>Realiſts</hi> themſelves do not diſſemble their Tritheiſm.</head>
               <p>MY next Obſervation on them, is; That <q rend="inline">themſelves do (ſometimes almoſt openly, and explicitely.) own and profeſs their Tritheiſm; both the Antients, and Moderns; both thoſe that hold the Equality of Perſons, and thoſe that deny it.</q> Let us take ſome Examples, of this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnobius</hi> calls the Father, and in contradiſtinction to the Son, Deum Principem, <hi>the principal God;</hi> he calls the Son, <hi>Deum ex Principis Dei juſſione loquentem, The God who ſpeaks by the Commandment of the chief God.</hi> l.2. p. 81. But can it ever be avoided; that <hi>a principal</hi> God, and <hi>a leſs principal</hi> God, who ſpeaks only by command from <hi>the chief God,</hi> are too Gods?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> calls the Son, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46702:14"/>God who is Servant, to God the maker of all things.</hi> Dialog. cum Tryph. pag. 279. Are not <hi>God the Servant,</hi> and the <hi>God to whom he is Servant,</hi> moſt certainly two Gods? do not theſe Predications manifeſtly ſuppoſe and imply them to be diſtinct Gods: can the ſame God in number, be ſaid to be Servant and Lord; and that too (as they ſpeak) <hi>ad Idem,</hi> or <hi>ad Eundem, with reſpect to the ſame thing or to himſelf?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Origen</hi> yet more expreſly; <hi>we call the Son, the ſecond God.</hi> Cont. Celſ. l.5. p. 258. And again, <hi>the firſt God</hi> (or the Father) <hi>worketh not; no nor properly ſpeaking doth the</hi> (Son or) <hi>ſecond God.</hi> Cont. Celſ. l. 6. p. 318. Shall not a <hi>firſt</hi> and a <hi>ſecond God</hi> be allowed to be two Gods; could this Father more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare his Tritheiſm?</p>
               <p>I grant, that <hi>Origen</hi> and all the Ante-Nicens, were ſuch Realiſts, as held <hi>the Inequality</hi> of the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons; but ſtill they believed them to be ſo many Gods. <hi>Origen</hi> was is much of Opinion, that the Son is inferiour to the Father; that (with <hi>Arius</hi>) he will not allow him to be <hi>truly Co eternal,</hi> but only the <hi>oldeſt of the Creatures,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith he, <hi>contr. Celf.</hi> l. 5, p. 257.) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And he is ſo far from thinking that the Son is <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty;</hi> that he every where denies that he may be Prayed to: except only as to a Mediator, who (ſaith he) is to Pray <hi>with</hi> us, and <hi>for</hi> us. <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi>'s firſt and 2d Books concerning Prayer, have ſo many Arguments di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt Praying to any but the Father; and particularly that we ſhould not Pray to the Son, he calls them <hi>Fools</hi> that do: that it well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears indeed, he held Father and Son to be <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts do; and that he durſt ſay, there are two Gods, a <hi>firſt</hi> and a <hi>ſecond</hi> God: but yet that in Truth, the Supream Divinity (or <hi>true Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>) is in the Father only. Which alſo is the Opinion of all the Ante-Nicens, and was the Doctrine that <hi>Arius</hi> (afterwards) maintained: with whom, thoſe Modern Realiſts who hold the Inequality, do (almoſt) wholly ſymbolize; it may be ſaid, that moſt of thoſe who hold the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of the ſuppoſed three Divine (ſubſiſting) Perſons, perfectly agree with the <hi>Ariani molles, the moderate Arians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here comes one, that will make all the World to know the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thoughts of the Realiſts; he perfectly (and in terms) diſcovers their Secret. 'Tis St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> called by his Party of Realiſts <hi>(who hold the Inequality)</hi> Baſilius Magnus, <hi>Baſil the Great,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline">To thoſe, <hi>(ſaith this bold Man)</hi> who accuſe us, as hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three Gods; we anſwer: <hi>God is not one, in Number,</hi> but only in Nature.</q> He means, as the Nature of Man, namely, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Humanity, is one; but there are many <hi>particular Men,</hi> Peter, James, John, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Nature of God, or the common Divinity is one; but there are as truly more Gods in number, or more <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46702:14"/>Gods,</hi> as there are more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Men; Father, Son and Spirit are each of them as truly a God, as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> are each of them a particular Man. This fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Paſſage is to be found in <hi>Baſil</hi>'s 141ſt Epiſtle, <hi>ad Caeſarienſes.</hi> Again <hi>(Adv. Eunom.)</hi>
                  <q rend="inline">In the Number and in the Properties, there is a Diverſity or Multiplicity; in the Properties by which each Divine Perſon is characteriz'd, we believe a Diverſity; and <hi>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, only in what makes the Deity.</hi>
                  </q> i.e. In the Divine Attributes, that are common to all the three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: for each Perſon has Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Omnipotence, and Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, perfect Goodneſs; which At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes make the Deity, as <hi>Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> and <hi>Riſibility</hi> make the Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Baſil</hi> then held; that to this Queſtion, <hi>how many Gods,</hi> it muſt be anſwered: <hi>three Gods in Number,</hi> or <hi>three Perſonal Gods,</hi> and one in Nature or Divine Properties. Which is to ſay; in very Deed, <hi>three Gods:</hi> but yet <hi>Gods ſo reſembling one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that from <hi>the ſameneſs</hi> of their Attributes or <hi>Eſſential</hi> (not Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) <hi>Properties,</hi> they may be called one God; even as <hi>all Men,</hi> or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from <hi>the ſameneſs</hi> of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, namely, the Rational, are in common ſpeech often times called <hi>Man.</hi> Which Compariſon, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of their Meaning and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is often uſed by St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen;</hi> the Patriarchs and Founders of thoſe Realiſts, who affirm the Equality of the (ſuppoſed) Divine <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſons.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Modern</hi> Realiſts, they are only ſome late Writers of our own Nation; the firſt and chief is Dr. <hi>Cudworth,</hi> after him followed Dr. <hi>Bull:</hi> then Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>How,</hi> Mr. <hi>Milbourn,</hi> Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> in his late (Learned and Bitter.) Anſwer to Dr. <hi>S—th.</hi> Some of theſe are for the abſolute Equality of the Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in all <hi>Eſſential</hi> Attributes; ſuch as Power, Wiſdom, Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: but ſome, as Dr. <hi>Cudworth</hi> eſpecially, will allow the Son and Spirit to be equal in nothing to the Father, but only that they are Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eternal; and by <hi>this,</hi> he thinks, he ſufficiently acquits himſelf of Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm. But both Parties moſt open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avow their Tritheiſm; and that many ways. By ſaying; there are three infinite <hi>Spirits,</hi> three Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient <hi>Minds,</hi> three Divine intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual <hi>Subſtances;</hi> three Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>as really Subſiſting,</hi> and as truly Diſtinct and divers, as three Angels or three Men are. Again, by their Explication of the Poſſibility, and the Manner, of an Unity in Trinity. Some of them ſaving; three <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> Divine Perſons are one God, by a certain moſt cloſe Unition of their Subſtances; Others, by mutual Conſciouſneſs, of one another's Thoughts and Actions; or becauſe, beſides their having <hi>like Subſtances and Properties,</hi> they are alſo <hi>in</hi> one another. They ſee nor, what 'tis marvellous Men of their Senſe ſhould not ſee; that ſeveral <hi>ſubſiſting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:46702:15"/>each of which is a perfect God, three Almighties, three Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, whether <hi>Conſcious,</hi> or <hi>not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious</hi> to one another, whether <hi>in</hi> or <hi>out of</hi> one another, whether <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or at <hi>odds,</hi> none of theſe Foreign Conſiderations can <hi>ſo alter</hi> the Caſe, but that all Three muſt as truly be three perfect Gods, as each of them (is confeſſed) to be one perfect God.</p>
               <p>But let us hear Mr. <hi>J. S.</hi> in his late Anſwer to Dr. <hi>S—th</hi>'s Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions on Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi> For as this Gentleman is well skilled in theſe Queſtions; ſo he delivers his Mind without much Reſerve: he ſeems not to be afraid, to ſay what he thinks; becauſe 'tis ſo certain, that the Fathers (after the Year 380.) were in the very ſame Sentiments concerning the Trinity; namely, that the Perſons of the Trinity arc really diſtinct and <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> and equally have all Divine Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in the higheſt Degree. He faith, <hi>pag.</hi> 141. <q rend="inline">Each <hi>diſtinct</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon, is as compleatly and perfectly God; as each <hi>diſtinct</hi> Angdical Perſon is a compleat perfect Angel.</q> He demands at <hi>pag.</hi> 75. <q rend="inline">Will the Animadverter (Dr. <hi>S—th</hi>) deny; that one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon is one God?</q> I will anſwer for Dr. <hi>S—th.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,</hi> to ſay; that the Perſons of the Trinity are as diſtinct, as three An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Perſons: for Angels or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Perſons are diſtinguiſhed in their Subſtances, and have ſo many ſeveral Underſtandings, Wills and Energies; but in all theſe Reſpects, the Perſons of the Trinity are not diſtinct, but are (Identically) the ſame. Nor is one Perſon of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>as compleatly and perfectly God;</hi> as an Angelical Perſon is compleatly and perfectly an Angel: for one Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Perſon is a compleat and perfect Angel; but all three Perſons of the Trinity, and not one only, are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to compleat the Notion and due Conception of one God. Therefore to his Queſtion, Is not one Divine Perſon one God ? I anſwer, no; three Divine Perſons are one God: that is to ſay, taking the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> in the Senſe that the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it, namely, for <hi>Relative Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> or the threefold Relation of the Deity. But taking a Divine Perſon, as this Author and his Fellow-Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts do, for a <hi>ſubſiſting Perſon,</hi> a diſtinct intellectual Being, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mind and Spirit; I anſwer, and the Church alſo ſo anſwers: that indeed every ſuch Perſon is one God, and three ſuch are three Gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 85. <q rend="inline">When God is ſaid to be three Perſons, the term God is taken in a Logical Senſe; and is equivalent to a <hi>terminus Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> or a <hi>Species.</hi>
                  </q> As who ſhould ſay; there are truly three Gods, in a proper, phyſical, and natural Senſe of the word <hi>God:</hi> for the words. <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> are <hi>ſpecifical</hi> Terms; the <hi>former</hi> implies divers (perſonal) Gods, as the <hi>other</hi> implies many (perſonal and individual) Men. He is ſo far from being aſhamed of all this; that he adds again,</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:46702:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 85. <q rend="inline">The Fathers of the Nicene Council, nay the whole Eaſtern Church did appropriate a the title <hi>one God</hi> to the Father; and <hi>God of God</hi> to the Son.</q> The Fathers meant thereby, the Son is God (not of or from himſelf, but) <hi>from,</hi> or <hi>by,</hi> or <hi>of</hi> the Father. See what uſe Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> makes of this, at <hi>pag.</hi> 91. <q rend="inline">The Phraſe <hi>God of God</hi> does neceſſarily imply a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of the term <hi>God,</hi> in ſome Senſe or other. And one and the ſame numerical <hi>God (in concreto)</hi> can never be <hi>God of God</hi> and <hi>not God of God:</hi> theſe two cannot be verified of the ſame <hi>Subject;</hi> of <hi>one and the ſame God, in concreto,</hi> or <hi>in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> 
                  </q> 'Tis Hereſy <hi>in excelſis;</hi> and the laſt words <hi>in Perſon,</hi> deſigned only <hi>to blind</hi> his true meaning, or <hi>to mollifie</hi> it to thoſe that happen to underſtand him, do but increaſe the groſſneſs of his Tritheiſm. He hath ſaid (in thoſe words) in effect; the Nicene Creed, and Oriental Church acknowledging one who is <hi>God of God,</hi> this God (who is God <hi>of,</hi> or <hi>from</hi> God) cannot be the ſame God with him <hi>from</hi> or <hi>of</hi> whom he is God, namely, with God the Father: theſe two muſt be <hi>ſeveral Subjects, different Gods.</hi> This avowed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, I ſay, is neither hid nor ſofmed by adding; <hi>different Gods, in concreto, or in Perſon:</hi> for it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid (or ſo much as thought) before, that the multiplication of Perſons in the Godhead, or theſe expreſſions, <hi>God the Father, God the Son, God the H. Spirit,</hi> would war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any one to ſay <hi>ſeveral Gods,</hi> or that <hi>God of God</hi> is not the ſame both Subject and God, with <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>God the Holy Spirit.</hi> In ſhort, that which this Author and his Party of Realiſts intend, and ſay, (though ſomewhat Covertly and Artificially) is; that as all the Men in the World, <hi>in concreto,</hi> are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſometimes expreſſed by the general <hi>abſtract</hi> word <hi>Man:</hi> So the three Gods, <hi>in concreto,</hi> three Perſonal (really ſubſiſting) Gods may alſo be expreſſed; but they care not how ſeldom, the ſeldomer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by that (ſcurvy, Socinian) <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract</hi> word <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have not made theſe (ſhort) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> with a malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Intention; to create Envy, or to raiſe up Enemies, to him: I ſhall confeſs, that as broadly as he has ſpoke; St. <hi>Saſil, Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> and other Fathers (after the Year 380) ſo Taught, and ſo Spoke; and I have before given ſome inſtances of it; as I ſhall give more, in the Continuation of my Anſwer to Dr. <hi>BuII</hi>'s <hi>Defence of the Nicene Faith,</hi> and <hi>Judgment of the Catholick Church.</hi> But all that I deſign, is only; to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the World, whether <hi>the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> have not notoriouſly owned and profeſſed their Tritheiſm, with which they are charged, not only by the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians, but by the Nominals; which is to ſay, by the Church. Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> is but one Man, he is only a private Doctor; but he has rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Doctrine of the Church: if a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46702:16"/>General Council were again to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, they would certainly eſpouſe his two Books; he hath ſaid neither more, nor leſs, nor otherwiſe, than the Catholick Church (ſince the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi>) has conſtantly taught. Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> is a Learned and very diſcerning Perſon, ſo are other <hi>Realiſts</hi> of this Nation (I muſt not ſay, of <hi>the Engliſh,</hi> or of <hi>the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Church, for they are departed from both) who have lately written againſt the Socinians: but they have oppoſed to ours, ſuch an Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the words <hi>God, Perſons, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> as Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> hath deſervedly called a Trinity of Gods; nor will they be ever able to wipe off the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> muſt not think, he has anſwered Dr. <hi>S—th:</hi> he hath only, ſometimes miſtaken him; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times miſreported, or perverted, his plain and obvious Meaning; or quarrelled with the Doctrine of the Schools, and of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, (which is to ſay, of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church) to make room for the (exploded) Tritheiſm of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and ſome other Fathers.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of the Catholick Church, Mr. <hi>J.B.</hi> knows well, can be fetched only from <hi>General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils;</hi> the Church is never underſtood to ſpeak, but by a General Council: particular Fathers are but only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Doctors; they are not the Church, how many ſoever they are. Therefore I deſire Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> to tell me, what Council ever uſed his Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; that one Divine Perſon is one God, as perfectly one God, as one Angelical Perſon is one perfect Angel? In what Council ſhall we find, that the word <hi>God</hi> is equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to <hi>a Species;</hi> which is to ſay, the <hi>Divinity</hi> no leſs than the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity</hi> (or the Manhood) compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends ſeveral Individuals, of the ſame both Nature and Denomination: as there are many Men, <hi>in concreto,</hi> ſo there are divers Gods alſo, <hi>in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto.</hi> Can he direct us to that Council, which teaches; that <hi>God of God,</hi> and <hi>God not of God</hi> (that is, Father and Son) are not the ſame God; or that the term <hi>God</hi> implies any Multiplication? Did ever any Council ſo far apoſtatize from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as to deny; that there is <hi>but one numerical God:</hi> and call that Doctrine <hi>the Faith of Jews, Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, and Heathens?</hi> But this is Mr. <hi>J.B</hi>'s Language, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of all the Realiſts; they all intend as he has ſaid: nor will any of them cenſure his Book, but applaud it as a great and extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. I do not regard the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences of Mr. <hi>Tho. Holdſworth</hi> (of <hi>North-Stoneham,</hi> near <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) in his late <hi>Impar Conatui,</hi> which he hath oppoſed to Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> This <hi>Orlando</hi> has vomited up his Crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, on a Perſon too much above him to take notice of him; and all that I ſhall trouble my ſelf to ſay of him, is: that if, as he has been careful to tell us the Place of his Reſidence, and of his Vicinage, ſo he had alſo told us <hi>his Age;</hi> we might have gueſſed, with more certainty than now we well can, whether he <hi>raves,</hi> or <hi>dotes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46702:16"/>
               <head>The <hi>Realiſts</hi> ſpeak much more Myſtically, or Abſurdly, than the <hi>Nominals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Muſt make another Remark on the Realiſts; namely: That the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd contradictory and impoſſible Things, partly expreſty ſaid by 'em, partly implied in their Doctrine, are far leſs tolerable or accountable; than the (forced) Improprieties, in the uſe of Words and Terms, by the Nominals, are.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, both Parties ſo often depart, from the common uſe of Terms and Words; that one as well as the other is frequently forced, to the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Myſtery:</hi> when they cannot aſſoil the Difficulties, objected to themſelves by each other, or by the <hi>Socinians</hi> to both; when they find that the uſe of <hi>Words,</hi> and the nature of <hi>Things,</hi> are both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they cry Myſtery; their Doctrine then (they confeſs) though a Truth, is however a Myſtery, above the Capacity, whether of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or of any others. But then, ſay I; the Realiſts would cover ſuch <hi>flat</hi> Impoſſibilities, ſuch <hi>groſs</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions to common Senſe, in a Word ſuch Monſtroſities, under the cloak of <hi>Myſtery:</hi> that they have infinitely more need of that (wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Blind, than the Nominals; who only <hi>by explaining their Terms,</hi> which Cuſtom and Law have impoſed on them, go a great way in fairly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying all Difficulties; and when they cannot perfectly account for them, they make ſome ſmall uſe of <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</hi> To underſtand this; we muſt take a ſhort view, of the (polite, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py) Things, ſaid by them both.</p>
               <p>The Nominals teach, there is but one, (numerical) God, or <hi>one God in Number;</hi> who yet is <hi>three Perſons.</hi> That the Father is God, the Son is God, the H. Ghoſt is God; yet all three are but one God, one God <hi>in Number,</hi> one <hi>ſelf-ſame God.</hi> They are perfectly aware, this were equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impoſſible and Ridiculous; if 'twere not dextrouſly interpreted and explained: it would not be My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, or <hi>Myſterious Truth,</hi> but <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Falſhood</hi> and Abſurdity, they well know; if wholly left in theſe Terms, without an Explication. Therefore they declare, that by the term <hi>Perſons,</hi> and the words <hi>Father, Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> they mean not (with the Vulgar) ſeveral <hi>ſubſiſting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> that is to ſay, <q rend="inline">So many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual Subſtances, with each his own particular Life, Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Will, and power of Action;</q> for they confeſs there is in God but one Subſtance, Life, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will, Energy, <hi>in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber:</hi> but three <hi>Perſons</hi> in God are ſo many <hi>States,</hi> or <hi>Reſpects,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties,</hi> or <hi>Relations</hi> (or ſomething equivalent to theſe) of the ſame ore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46702:17"/>Divine intellectual Subſtance or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And in this Senſe alſo, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Nominals, the words Father, Son and Spirit (when uſed of God) are to be underſtood: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as <hi>Relations</hi> or <hi>States,</hi> all of them ſuſtained by one and the ſame <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſon,</hi> or <hi>intellectual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> not as in ſo many Subjects, or as denominating variouſly three diſtinct Beings. They ſhow, that ſo the Claſſical Authors, both Greek and Latin, ſpoke: and as their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage was adopted by the Church, in ſpeaking of God, with great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety; ſo in proceſs of Time, the uſe of Words being much altered, occaſion was given to introduce the Hereſy of the Realiſts; who unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly underſtanding the old Words, in a novel Senſe, have brought into the Church three Gods, inſtead of one.</p>
               <p>Again, they (the Nominals) ſay, the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity (or of God) <hi>was Incarnate</hi> in the Man Chriſt Jeſus; in ſuch manner, that thereby the Lord Chriſt is <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>Man.</hi> This alſo is called by that Myſtical Name, the Hypoſtatical (or perſonal) Union. But they mean no more by it, than this; that God was as much and truly united to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, as the Human Nature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of: that is to ſay, in a moſt extraordinary, marvellous, and (to us) unaccountable Manner.</p>
               <p>When they ſay, O God the Father have Mercy on us; O God the Son, O God the Holy Ghoſt, have Mercy on us; they intend not hereby <hi>three Objects of Worſhip,</hi> or ſo many <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Patrons</hi> and Helpers: but only as theſe are ſo many Relations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of the Deity, either to himſelf or to us; ſo they invocate him by theſe Diſtinctions, or in theſe ſeveral Properties and Relations. In ſhort, the whole Myſtery conſiſts in the Terms they uſe; and ſcarce at all, if at all in the Senſe, or things intended by thoſe Terms: which things (or ſenſe) are received, and imbraced by us the Unitarians; for we admit the whole Doctrine, as here declared and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</p>
               <p>But 'tis quite otherwiſe with the Realiſts; their Non-ſenſe is in <hi>the thing</hi> meant, not in <hi>the Words</hi> or Terms. They ſay, there are three Divine <hi>ſubſiſting Perſons,</hi> three infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>Spirits,</hi> three omniſcient <hi>Minds,</hi> three <hi>diſtinct</hi> Almighties, as diſtinct as ſo many Angels or Men; each of them as truly, properly, adequately, and perfectly God, as each Man is a Man, and each Angel an Angel: and yet all of them are but one God. This, we confeſs, is <hi>Myſtery</hi> with a Witneſs; the Myſtery (every one ſees) lies not in <hi>the Words</hi> and <hi>Terms,</hi> but <hi>the thing</hi> it ſelf is abſurd and impoſſible: to cry <hi>Myſtery</hi> here, is to profeſs; that by Myſtery, we mean <hi>Contradiction,</hi> and Impoſſibilities.</p>
               <p>The Excuſes they make for this Myſtery, are as myſterious, or more myſterious than the Myſtery, for which they would apologize. For to ſay, theſe three (moſt perfect) Gods become one God, <hi>by their mutual Accord and Love,</hi> is; as if you ſhould pretend, that by Love and Accord,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46702:17"/>three <hi>Men</hi> are one <hi>Man.</hi> And when they ſay, they are one God by like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or <hi>ſameneſs of Nature and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties;</hi> and by being <hi>in one another:</hi> they might equally ſay, that two or more Angels, becauſe they have <hi>the ſame Nature and Properties,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spiritual, do immeate, or are <hi>in one another,</hi> are thereby one Angel. Theſe Explications of their Myſtery, are aſſuredly as great Myſteries, as direct Contradictions to Reaſon and common Experience; as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine it ſelf, of one God and three Divine <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> Perſons. But why do the Realiſts expect, that Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind will be perſwaded to accept ſuch palpable abnegations of all conſiſtent Senſe, for <hi>Myſtery:</hi> words that are hardly Senſe, or of either ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or obſcure meaning, may be put off (with ſome or other, who care not for the Trouble of conſidering) for Myſtery; but <hi>groſs</hi> Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>obvious</hi> and <hi>notorious</hi> Non-ſenſe, will never be miſtaken for Myſtery. 'Tis true, People may be conſtrained to profeſs it, or to ſubſcribe to it; but they never believe it, no not when (through a long habit of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Commands of others) they ſeem to themſelves to believe it. I doubt not, that the Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeem to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to believe the Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe having accuſtom'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſubmit to the Declarations of the Church, they have never ſuffered any reluctance to ariſe in their Minds, againſt any of thoſe. Declarations: notwithſtanding, I am perſwaded, not a Man of them truly believes that Myſtery; were all Fears and Hopes, and other blaſſing Intereſts removed, they would preſently perceive, that in very Deed they believe it not; <hi>their Reaſons never aſſented to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible Proportion, nor could aſſent;</hi> but only (as I ſaid) through a long habit of Submiſſion, <hi>they did not diſcern,</hi> that they aſſented not to the Church's Declarations. And this, I believe, is true alſo, of all who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, or ſeem to believe any other inconſiſtent, or impoſſible Doctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Tritheiſm of the <hi>Realiſts,</hi> not grounded on the H. Scripture.</head>
               <p>BUT this once more; 'tis not on a probable or prudent Ground, that the Realiſts ſometimes pretend, that the Tritheiſm they impoſe has ſuch a Foundation in Holy Scripture: that as on the one ſide, to believe the Trinity in their Notion of it, is a violence done to Reaſon; ſo not to own and profeſs it, would oblige them to as great a Violence, and Diſobedience to Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, I have often wondred; that Men ſo Learned and Diſcerning, as very many of the Realiſts are, ſhould maintain ſuch an Opinion; and after having made ſuch Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to the Nominals, and to the Unitarians, as the Realiſts do. They
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46702:18"/>grant it, to be certain and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, not only in Reaſon, but in Holy Scripture, that there is but one God, but one Creator; they allow this to be ſo true and evident, that the Scripture ought never to be ſo interpreted, as in any degree to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict this firſt Article of all revealed Religion: becauſe to interpret Holy Scripture at any Time, or in any part of it, inconſiſtently with that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, were to make it contradict it ſelf, and that too, where it ſpeaks moſt plainly and expreſly. I ſay, this Foundation being laid, and agreed on all Hands; I have often wondred at the pretence of the Realiſts: for their Doctrine being a manifeſt Tritheiſm, as explained by them; in ſaying 'tis what the Holy Scriptures teach, they ſay, that the Sacred Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelves. They would have it underſtood as a great deference, on their Parts, towards the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; that they imbrace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Doctrine therein contained, though ſuch Doctrine very flatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts all Reaſon and common Senſe, and withal other parts of the ſame Scriptures: but it were far more becoming ſuch as they are, to expreſs their Reverence for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by interpreting it conſiſtently with it ſelf, and with Reaſon, as the Nominals and Unitarians do; than to expoſe it to the contempt and unbelief of all others, by ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of it as this Book needs not; that is to ſay, by pretending to believe it indeed, but believe it <hi>as manifeſtly inconſiſtent with it ſelf;</hi> as well as with that Reaſon which God has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the Human Nature, for a Guide and Judg, in all either ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure or doubtful Matters. It is the Church and the Unitarians, that truly reverence the Scriptures; by reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from ſenſeleſs, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory (which is to ſay, impoſſible) Senſes.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing it were true, that the meer Words of ſome few (ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, or ambiguous) Texts, did ſeem very much to favour the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Realiſts; yet ſeeing thoſe Texts (as interpreted by the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts) too plainly contradict evident Reaſon, and the Nature of things: why will not theſe Gentlemen ſee, that in ſuch a Claſh as this, <q rend="inline">We <hi>muſt</hi> interpret the Scripture conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtently with Reaſon and the nature of things; becauſe <hi>words</hi> will bear to be ſomewhat ſtrained, much rather than <hi>things?</hi>
                  </q> The nature of Things, and the dictates of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are Eternal and Immutable; they will not admit, or bear the leaſt Stretch, Strain, or Violence done to them: but Words are of a very deſultory and vagrant Meaning; they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be taken Literally, or <hi>as they Sound,</hi> ſometimes in a metaphorical or <hi>figurative Senſe;</hi> ſometimes in an Hyperbolical, that is <hi>exceſſive;</hi> nay, ſometimes in an Ironical (which is to ſay, <hi>contrary</hi>) Senſe: which being the Caſe of all Books and Writings whatſoever, there can never be a real Neceſſity of ſo interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it ſhould contradict the <hi>known</hi> Nature of things, <hi>plain</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Whereas ſome ſay here, and are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46702:18"/>willing always to repeat it; that <hi>the current</hi> of Scripture is ſo much, and ſo clearly, for ſuch a Trinity as the Realiſts profeſs: that it would be manifeſt Violence, done to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Word, to interpret it as the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians do. I anſwer, <hi>Cedò locum, name me the Text,</hi> or Context, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; that is not interpreted by ſome of the moſt Learned Criticks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of the Trinitarian Party, in the ſame manner as 'tis underſtood by the Unitarians. Why do they pretend, that they are <hi>conſtrained,</hi> and by <hi>the clearneſs,</hi> and <hi>the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> of Scripture; to profeſs a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Divine <hi>(ſubſiſting)</hi> Perſons: when all Learned Men know, that the Texts they have to alledg, are ſo far from being <hi>the current</hi> of Scripture, that they are <hi>few in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and alſo of <hi>very ſuſpected Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> that is, they are juſtly doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, whether they are genuine ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Parts of Scripture, or have been added to it; and <hi>ſo far from being clear,</hi> that they are <hi>extreamly Ambiguous,</hi> and accordingly not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome, but even the generality of Trinitarian Criticks interpret <hi>moſt</hi> of them, as <hi>we</hi> do; and not only moſt of them, but the Principal of them, more particularly the (objected) Texts that ſeem to impute the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Things to our Saviour. As I ſaid but now, <hi>Cedò locum, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that Text,</hi> or Context, which I will not ſhow is interpreted by the moſt ſufficient of their own Party, as we take it: but if ſo, as 'tis not the firſt Time this Challenge has been made to them; why do they (ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly) pretend, that they are carried away by the Current of Scripture, and by the clearneſs of it, both on their ſides? May they call a few ſingle Texts (or rather, ſhreds of Texts the Current of Scripture: or talk of the clearneſs of their Texts; when they cannot alledg ſo much as one, but is interpreted to an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian Senſe by ſome of their own (beſt) Writers, on the Scriptures, and of Controverſy?</p>
               <p>With how much more Reaſon and Sincerity, may the Unitarians claim the current of Scripture; and that 'tis clear alſo, on their Side? For there is not a Page there, but ſpeaks of God <hi>in the ſingular Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> there God is never called <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> but <hi>Perſon:</hi> he is always ſpoken <hi>of,</hi> and <hi>to,</hi> by ſingular Pronouns, ſuch as <hi>I, Thou, Thee, He, Him, Me;</hi> which are never uſed in any Language, but only of one ſingle Perſon; never of three <hi>(ſubſiſting)</hi> Perſons.</p>
               <p>When the Realiſts ſay, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are <hi>clear</hi> of their ſide; they mean it chiefly of thoſe Texts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt is called <hi>God:</hi> and of thoſe, in which the Creation of the World, and of all things, is (or ſeems to be) attributed to him. But how often is the name <hi>God</hi> given in Holy Scripture, to thoſe that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repreſent God, as Kings and Magiſtrates; or that are like to him in ſome very diſtinguiſhing Reſpect, or in whom he dwells after a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner, as Prophets, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Perſons: is, not <hi>Moſes</hi> (for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46702:19"/>one Inſtance) on all theſe accounts called <hi>God,</hi> and by God himſelf? And is it a Marvel then, that the Mediator alſo of the New Teſtament, as well as he of the Old, is dignified with this Name? And yet (as I have ſaid elſewhere) I am well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that the Realiſts will never prove, againſt the Author of the Brief Hiſtory of the Socinians; that the name <hi>God</hi> is really given to the Lord Chriſt, in any Text that is a genuine Part of Scripture: that is to ſay, that hath not been corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Zeal of Catholicks, to make it more conformable to their Sentiments. As to the Texts, that impute the Creation of things, to the Son; that is, to the Lord Chriſt: do not all Learned Men know, that the beſt of the Trinitarian Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſome of the zealouſeſt Men of the Party, underſtand <hi>all</hi> thoſe Texts of <hi>the New Creation;</hi> that is, of the Renovation of things <hi>on Earth,</hi> by the Miniſtry of Chriſt; and <hi>in Heaven,</hi> by his Exaltation above the Angels? And ſecondly, That neither is there any need of <hi>this;</hi> for thoſe Texts may be thus tranſlated: all things were made <hi>for</hi> him; and <hi>without regard to him, was nothing made that was made.</hi> Were made <hi>for him;</hi> that is to ſay, they were originally made by God, <hi>for the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah:</hi> namely, to ſubject them (in fulneſs of Time) to <hi>him,</hi> and to <hi>his</hi> Law. Which is the Interpretation of St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> a moſt Learned Trinitarian, in the <hi>Opus Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectum,</hi> on St. <hi>Matthew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, I would not have it ſaid; that <hi>the current</hi> of Scripture <hi>is,</hi> much leſs is <hi>clearly,</hi> on their ſide, who contend for a Trinity of Divine <hi>(ſubſiſting)</hi> Perſons: becauſe 'tis ſo well known, that this (ſenſeleſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant) boaſt of ſome ſmall Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Controverſy, is the Jeſt and Sport of their own Criticks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of Note; who have far more ſcorn for ſuch Scioliſts, than they have Enmity to the Socinians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the <hi>Unitarians;</hi> their Agreement with the Church.</head>
               <p>THE Unitarians, called alſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians, are a Sect or Party, or Denomination of Chriſtians, who have indeavoured to perfect that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; that was ſo happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by Dr. <hi>M. Luther,</hi> Mr. <hi>J. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> and here (in <hi>England</hi>) by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Cranmer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Luther</hi> ſubverted the Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and Supremacy of the Pope; the Worſhip and Invocation of Angels, and Saints; the (ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious) monaſtick Vows; the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of Indulgencies, by which poor Sinners had been long cozen'd into a Belief, that they could buy the Pardon of their Sins, from the Pope and his Factors: and this not only without Reſtitution, Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Repentance, but <hi>without
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46702:19"/>Confeſſion;</hi> for that alſo was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Clauſe in their Bulls of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, that the Purchaſer ſhould be abſolved of <hi>all his Sins, whether Confeſſed or not Confeſſed.</hi> The forms of Indulgences were ſo ample, that is, ſo General and Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; that Men of any Wealth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cared, what Sins they were guilty of: becauſe they knew they could at any time, whether Dead or Alive, purchaſe their Pardon; if they had neglected it in their Life Time, 'twas but leaving ſo much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney by Will, for Maſſes and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, and they were ſure all ſhould be forgiven. The Story of the French Gentleman is well known; who being admoniſhed by his Friend, of his horrible Curſing and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; anſwered: <q rend="inline">Man, there is no fear, cannot I buy my Pardon of the Friars Auſtins? I would be forgiven for an Ounce of Gold, though I had raviſh'd the Mother of God, and cut off both her Breaſts.</q> This was the ſtate of Things, when Dr. <hi>Luther</hi> appeared, and oppoſed himſelf (ſo ſucceſsfully) to theſe Corruptions; as I ſaid, he intirely ruin'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Indulgences, Monaſtick Vows, Invocation of Saints and Angels, the Supremacy and Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Chair of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>J. Calvin,</hi> beſides that he greatly ſtrengthned, and confirmed what Dr. <hi>Luther</hi> had begun; by his extraordinary Erudition, fine Wit, and indefatigable Diligence, in all which Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> excelled the very greateſt of the firſt Reformers: he carried the Reformation ſomewhat farther, than <hi>Luther</hi> had done. He took away <hi>the uſe</hi> of Images, which can ſerve only for <hi>a ſnare</hi> to the Weak; and for <hi>an Avocation,</hi> and <hi>Amuſement,</hi> to the Diſcerning. His Doctrine concerning the Sacraments, has fewer Follies than, not only that of <hi>Rome,</hi> but, than <hi>Luthers;</hi> he rejected the Conſubſtantiation, as well as the Tranſubſtantiation, and was not impoſed on by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Ubiquity. I need ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Reformation is known to every Engliſhman: his Doctrine and Diſcipline being expreſſed in the 39 Articles, the Books of Homilies, of Canons, and the Common-Prayer.</p>
               <p>All Proteſtants have a great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, for theſe famous and excellent Men; even thoſe of us, who think, that their Reformation is yet very incompleat. I may add, that as much as theſe Reformers are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, by the Papiſts; the very Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, all Orders of them (from the higheſt to the loweſt; from the Pope, to the Begging, and diſcalceate Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar) are greatly in their Debt. For now they have Learned Prieſts, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Popes; and the Kings and States of the Roman Communion, are no longer the Slaves of the Pope: all which was otherways, when there were no Proteſtants, of whom the Pope and Conclave and (the reſt of their) Hierarchy might ſtand in ſome awe. The Popes conſider now; that they muſt act Soberly, live Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarily, and inſpect the Conduct
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46702:20"/>and Sufficiency of the Clergy; elſe the Princes and People, now in their Communion, will deſert to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</p>
               <p>It was Dr. <hi>Luther,</hi> as odious as his Name among them is; who took off the Yoke, and filed the Chains, from the Necks and Hands of Emperours, of Kings and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. From laying proſtrate, under the Feet of the Pope; from holding his Bridle, and his Stirrup; from expecting (after their Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Princes of the Empire) till the Pope ſhould pleaſe to crown them, and thereby give them the Name and Power of Emperours; from Trembling, every time that a (crouching) Friar was turned, into a (boiſterous) Pope: I ſay, from this miſerable Vaſſalage, the German Emperors, and other Catholick Kings and States, are delivered; and care now, juſt ſo much, and no more, for his <hi>Holineſs</hi>'s Love or Anger; as the Example of his Life, or the actual Aſſiſtance he can lend to 'em, ſhall merit. Since <hi>Luther, the Clergy</hi> (alſo) of the Roman Communion, are Learned and exemplary Men; in their own Defence, and for their own Security, they <hi>muſt be ſo.</hi> And they dare <hi>now,</hi> withſtand any new Incroachments on their Privileges, or their Revenues, by the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nay, they have retrieved, in ſome Degree, their antient Rights and Authority: for <hi>Rome</hi> dreads (and ever will dread) another <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> in caſe ſhe ſhould (unjuſtly, or raſhly) either oppreſs, or offend the inferior Clergy. Thoſe of <hi>the Lay-Communion</hi> of that Church, are <hi>now</hi> led with <hi>a Paſtoral-Staff;</hi> not hared with the Church's Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Excommunications</hi> and <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings up to Satan.</hi> They are ſent of no more Errands to <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Aſia;</hi> in pretence, to reſcue the Holy Sepulchre; in Deed, to inlarge the Papal Bounds, and Authority. They are fed now with much ſounder Doctrine; and led, by a better Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For now the neceſſity of Repentance, and Amendment, are taught; Indulgences are now owned, to be only Prudential and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble relaxations of Penance; Images are now uſed, only as Memorials of departed Saints, and Incentives to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate their Example; the Sacrifice of the Maſs is now only <hi>a commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Sacrifice,</hi> which even Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants believe it to be; the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> and the Saints are prayed to, only to pray <hi>with</hi> us, and <hi>for</hi> us: and the like abatement is made, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles. And whereas with reference to <hi>the Example</hi> of their Prieſts, it has been a Proverb in ſome Places; <q rend="inline">He that will give his Child to the Devil, let him make him a Prieſt: now,</q> and for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two Ages laſt paſt; their danger from the Proteſtants, as was ſaid before, has reformed their Manners.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Services, done by the firſt Reformers; as well to the Papiſts themſelves, as to us of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: their Memory is glorious, and ought to be precious alſo, among us. But we ſay alſo; that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>géan Stable was too foul, to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely cleanſed at once, even by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46702:20"/>
                  <hi>Hercules</hi> and his Companions: Dr. <hi>Luther</hi> did a great deal, the Labours of his Companions and Seconds were very laudable; but much Filth is ſtill left behind. We deſire to be (fairly and candidly) heard, concerning ſome corruptions in the Faith; and ſome abuſes in the Morality, ſtill taught: and particularly, which is the Subject of theſe preſent Papers, concerning the Object of our Faith and Worſhip, Almighty GOD.</p>
               <p>We ſee, we own; that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>the Church,</hi> meaning by the Church <hi>the Nominal Trinitarians,</hi> is ſound, as to the <hi>Senſe and Intention of it:</hi> but we (humbly) offer, that <hi>the Terms</hi> in which 'tis expreſſed, are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptural,</hi> and <hi>very Dangerous.</hi> The words <hi>Trinity, Incarnation, Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> are never uſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; nor is God ever there called <hi>Perſons,</hi> but <hi>Perſon.</hi> And 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that by occaſion of theſe Terms; the Vulgar have ſuch a conception of the Trinity, as is <hi>certain Tritheiſm.</hi> When the People hear of God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt; they know not, that thereby are meant only ſo many <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> of God, either <hi>internal</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to himſelf, or <hi>external</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Creature: but they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in their Minds, ſuch a Father, Son and Spirit diſtinct from both, as are ſo many ſeveral ſubſiſting Spirits, ſo many diſtinct All-perfect Beings; in very Deed ſo many <hi>Living Gods,</hi> and not <hi>one God under three ſeveral Conceptions.</hi> For tho they are taught to ſay, three Divine Perſons and <hi>but one God;</hi> and that God the Father, God his Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, tho each of them is God, yet <hi>all of them are but one God:</hi> this laſt <hi>all of them but one God,</hi> becauſe they know not how 'tis to be conceived with the other (namely, that each of them is God; and <hi>one</hi> of them is God the Father, <hi>another</hi> God the Son;) they utterly loſe the Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>one God,</hi> and retain only what is intelligible to them, namely, <hi>three Divine Perſons, each of them a God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We think, that the Church having gained her Point, againſt the Fathers and Realiſts, in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; and having been in Poſſeſſion of the Truth, for near 500 Years together: ſhe may now fling off the Diſguiſe hitherto uſed, the dangerous Tritheiſtick terms, <hi>Trinity, Perſons,</hi> and the reſt; ſhe may now begin to declare the Truth ſhe owns, in Terms and Words that are proper for it. Why does ſhe frown upon thoſe, nay, perſecute them, that believe the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God in the Senſe that ſhe holds it; only becauſe they would caſt out the Terms that ſo plainly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Tritheiſts, that is, <hi>the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts?</hi> What has the Church to fear; has not the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, and all Writers ever ſince, declared the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts to be Hereticks: therefore what need is there to retain their <hi>Terms,</hi> when we have diſcharged <hi>the Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> intended by them?</p>
               <p>'Tis true, we can ſay as the Church does, three Divine Perſons; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God, the Son is God, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is God; taking theſe words in the Church's Senſe, not for <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſons,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Living,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46702:21"/>Spirits,</hi> but for Relations, Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Modes, or ſuch like. We can ſay, <hi>God was Incarnate;</hi> meaning he did inhabit the Lord Chriſt, after an ineffable manner, and without Meaſure: which is really as much as the Church intends by the word In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation. We own the (eternal) Generation of the Son or <hi>Word,</hi> and Proceſſion of the Spirit, by and from the Father; explaining our ſelves, with the School-Divines, the Church, and divers Fathers, thus: that God or the Father, or original Wiſdom, conceived a moſt perfect Image of himſelf, <hi>by underſtanding,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his own Perfections; and that he <hi>loveth</hi> (or willeth) as well as underſtandeth himſelf. We can even ſay, three Divine <hi>ſubſiſting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> intending with Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> the Schools, the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, and the Church, <hi>Relative Subſiſtences, whoſe Subſiſtence is nothing elſe but their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> Which are Dr. <hi>S—th</hi>'s expreſs words, <hi>Tritheiſm charged,</hi> p. 156.</p>
               <p>I cannot but ask it again; why does the Church <hi>keep,</hi> or impoſe on <hi>us,</hi> ſuch Words and Terms; as in their <hi>preſent Signification,</hi> deſtroy the Faith we both imbrace; the Faith of <hi>the real <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God?</hi> We can ſay as the Church ſays, we can uſe her <hi>Terms;</hi> becauſe we know her mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but we cannot but ſay of them, as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> did (when ask'd his Opinion) of the Engliſh Common-Prayers, <hi>Tolerabiles Ineptiae.</hi> For in very Deed, 'tis meer Trifling, and ſomething worſe; when the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of theſe Terms and Words is wholly altered, from what it anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently was, yet ſtill to retain them: while the Church knows at the ſame Time, that they give wrong Notions to the Vulgar, making all our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Tritheiſts; and ſerve alſo to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and harden the Realiſts in their Hereſy.</p>
               <p>But I muſt do the Church this right, to confeſs; that moſt of her greateſt Men, particularly the firſt Reformers, have publiſh'd to all the World their hearty deſire, that all theſe terms of the Realiſts were aboliſh'd; and all were obliged to uſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Language and Words only: which would heal all our Breaches, and perfectly reſtore our Peace; not only in this, but in (almoſt) all other Queſtions and Strifes. Let us hear, of ſo many as might be alledged, Dr. <hi>M. Luther,</hi> and Mr. <hi>J. Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Luther</hi> complains; <q rend="inline">The word <hi>Trinity</hi> ſounds odly: it were better to call Almighty God, <hi>God;</hi> than <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
                  </q> Poſtil. major. Dominic.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> is yet leſs pleaſed, with theſe kind of Terms; he ſays, <q rend="inline">I like not this Prayer, <hi>O Holy Bleſſed and Glorious Trinity.</hi> It ſavours of Barbarity;—the word <hi>Trinity</hi> is bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous, inſipid, profane, an human Invention, grounded on no Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God's Word, the Popiſh God, unknown to the Prophets and Apoſtles.</q> 
                  <hi>Admon.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Polon.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <date>Decemb. 17. 1695.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46702:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
